<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A briefe treatise of oathes exacted by ordinaries and ecclesiasticall iudges, to answere generallie to all such articles or interrogatories, as pleaseth them to propound And of their forced and constrained oathes ex officio, wherein is proued that the same are vnlawfull.</title>
            <author>Morice, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07722</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18106</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112894</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99848135</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99848135</idno>
            <idno type="VID">13213</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07722)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 13213)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 480:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A briefe treatise of oathes exacted by ordinaries and ecclesiasticall iudges, to answere generallie to all such articles or interrogatories, as pleaseth them to propound And of their forced and constrained oathes ex officio, wherein is proued that the same are vnlawfull.</title>
                  <author>Morice, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>58, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By James Morice.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18107 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Oaths --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ecclesiastical courts --  Great Britain --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:13213:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13213:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13213:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:13213:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A briefe treatiſe of Oathes exacted by Ordinaries and Eccleſiaſticall Iudges, to anſwere generallie to all ſuch Articles or Interrogatories, as pleaſeth them to propound. And of their forced and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained Oathes <hi>ex officio,</hi> wherein is proued that the ſame are vnlawfull.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:13213:3"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:13213:3"/>
            <head>A briefe treatiſe of Oathes, exacted by Ordinaries and Eccleſiaſticall Iudges, to aunſwere generallie to all ſuch Articles or Interrogarories as pleaſeth them to propound. <hi>And of their forced and constrained Oathes</hi> ex officio, <hi>wherein is proued that the ſame are vnlawfull.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as the matter whereof we meane to intreate is concerning Oathes. It will bee verie neceſſarie for the better vnderſtanding thereof, firſte to conſider what an oath is, and the nature thereof: By whom it was inſtituted, and to what vſe, end and purpoſe: How many kindes of lawfull oathes there are, &amp; howe they ought to behaue themſelues that eyther require or receyue an oath.</p>
            <p>An Oath therefore (as learned Diuines haue defined) is a calling or takinge to recorde or witneſſe of the ſacred Name of God, or of God him ſelfe by the vſe of his holie Name, for the confirmation of the trueth of ſuch thinges which we ſpeake, or for the true performance of our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Or more brieflie: An oath is a confirmation of the will of man by the teſtimonie of God.</p>
            <p>The ſame of his owne nature, in aſmuch as it proceedeth from a right faith is verie good, for thereby wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge all things to bee thoroughlie knowen vnto God, and that he is a louer of trueth, and a reuenger of perjurie. It ſerueth alſo to the honor of Almightie God, becauſe ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by we extoll and magnifie his moſt holie Name,
<note place="margin">Hebrewes cap. 6. Deuterono. cap. 6.13.</note> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe the excellencie of his great Majeſtie: for that men ſweare by him that is greater. It is a part of his diuine ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, and commanded by him. And the ſame is to be vſed onely for the ſetting forth of the glorie of God, and for the profite and benefite of men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:13213:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> thereof was from and by God him ſelf, for the helpe and reliefe of our neceſſitie, eyther for the Aſſurance of ſuch dueties, couenauntes, contractes &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes as we owe or make: or to procure faith or credit (cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of proofe fayling) to the trueth which wee affirme: That an end of controuerſies may be had. For (as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the ſame chapter of the Epiſtle to the Hebrewes) An oath for confirmation is amongſt men <hi>An ende of all ſtrife.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="explanation">
               <head>Oathes are of two ſortes, that is to ſay, <hi>priuate and publique.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Priuate oathes are made betweene priuate perſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their particular affaires. As for th'aſſurance of du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, couenauntes, agreementes or promiſes, or to procure faith and credite to be giuen to that which is ment to bee perſwaded. Of which kinde of oathes wee haue many ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples in the ſacred Hiſtories, as in the booke of <hi>Geneſis</hi> cap. 24. and cap. 31. 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> cap. 20. 1. <hi>Regum</hi> cap. 18. <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</hi> cap. 38. and many other whiche for breuities ſake I omitte.</p>
               <p>Publique oathes are of diuers and ſundrie ſortes. As where Kings and Princes ſweare for the eſtabliſhment of their leagues and concluſions of peace.</p>
               <p>Or where the Prince and people ſweare eache to other: The Prince to rule and reigne juſtlie: The people in due al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leageaunce to obey faithfullie. This kinde of oathe was vſed 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> cap. 5. betweene <hi>Dauid</hi> the king &amp; th'Elders of Iſrael. In the booke of Iudges we read alſo howe th'El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of <hi>Gilead</hi> ſware ſubjection vnto <hi>Iephtah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>An other kinde of publique oathe we ſee 2. <hi>Cron.</hi> cap. 15 where king <hi>Aſa</hi> made the people of Iſrael to take an oath for the true worſhip and ſcruice of Almightie God, and the obſeruation of his Lawe. An oath not much different was that in <hi>Ezra</hi> cap. 10.</p>
               <p>That is alſo a publique oath whiche the Magiſtrates, Iudges and Officers of Iuſtice take for the true and ſincere
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:13213:4"/>adminiſtration of the Lawe. So is alſo the oath of Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours and men of warre, ſwearing obedience to their Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls, Captaines and Commaunders.</p>
               <p>An other kinde of publique oath is that likewiſe which the Iudge or Magiſtrate miniſtreth vnto ſuch as are called to depoſe and teſtifie the trueth in cauſes of ſuite and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, depending in Courtes or places of Iuſtice.</p>
               <p>And that alſo which either of the aduerſaries take in the ſame ſuites, or the defendant for the finall ending and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetmination of the controuerſie, which of ſome is termed a judiciall oath, and being offred by the defendant, it is of neceſsitie to the plaintife, for that hee cannot refuſe to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Of this laſt ſorte, among the lawes Iudiciall it is written thus:
<note place="margin">Exod. ca. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> If any man deliuer to his neigh bout to keepe Affe or Oxe or Sheepe, or any beaſt, and it dye or be hurt, or be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by force, &amp; no man ſee it, An oath of the Lord ſhalbe the meane betwene them twaine, that he put not his hand vnto his neighbours good, And the owner of it ſhall ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the oath, and the other ſhall not make it good.</p>
               <p>Concerning him that is to take an oath,
<note place="margin">The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent.</note> he is taught by the holy Ghoſt firſt to ſweare in trueth. That is to ſay true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie without falſhood, deceipt, or diſſimulation, the heart &amp; mouth agreeing in one:
<note place="margin">Hiere. ca. 4.</note> for ſince God is the authour and louer of trueth, and the Diuell is a lyar, and the father of lies, there can not be a greater diſhonour or indignitie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred to the ſacred Maieſtie of God, then to make his moſt fearfull and reuerende name, a witneſſe of falſhoode or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt, neither let any man thinke that by craftie or ſubtill ſwearing he can auoyde the deteſtable ſinne of perjurie. For <hi>fraus distringit non diſſoluit perjurium,</hi> fraude ſtrayneth harder, it diſſolueth not the perjurie as the learned <hi>Tullie</hi> verie well ſaide.</p>
               <p>Secondlie,
<note place="margin">Hier. ca. 4.</note> he that taketh an oath ought to ſweare in judgement, that is to ſaye, with good diſcretion, ſoberlie, well aduiſed and aſſured of that he wil affirme or denie vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his oath, Not ignorauntlie, raſhlie, vainlie, or in cauſes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:13213:5"/>of no moment or neceſſitie for ſuch vaine and fooliſh ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring is expreſlie forbidden by the commandement, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in alſo God threatneth, That he will not holde him guilt les, that taketh his name in vaine, that is, wil ſurelie puniſh him that ſo abuſeth his name. The ſame alſo in the newe Teſtament is by Chriſt him ſelfe condemned. Moreouer the holy Ghoſt by the Preacher well aduiſeth euerie man not to be raſhe with his mouth, nor to ſuffer his heart to be haſtie to vtter any thing before God, for that (ſayeth hee) God is in the Heauens, and thou art on the earth.</p>
               <p>In juſtice or righteouſnes alſo ought an oath to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, that is in things juſt and lawfull, not repugnaunt to the will or commaundement of God. For although it be true that is ſaide, <hi>Non est obligatorium contra bonos mores praestitum iuramentum,</hi> yet by ſwearing to doe the thinge that is vnjuſt or vnlawfull, the glorious name of God is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhonored. And ſuch a ſpeach ſaieth <hi>Eccleſiasticus,</hi> is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with death. Brieflie, the reſpect of euery de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponent ſhould be, that God by his oath may be magnified, the trueth in queſtion confirmed, juſtice maintained, and that Innocentes (by fraudulent practizes circumvented) may be freed and deliuered from perill and daunger.</p>
               <p>Touching ſuch as haue power and authoritie to require or commaunde an oath,
<note place="margin">The Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate.</note> they ought alſo to bee verie care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and circumſpect that they impoſe not the ſame but in cauſes of waight and neceſſitie, which is neuer to bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended but when the honour and glory of God is to bee maintayned, or the good of the common wealth, or of our neighbour furthered. For if it be a Principle <hi>De minimit non curat lex,</hi> by good reaſon the Magiſtrates and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of lawe ſhould ſpare to vſe that whiche is moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and precious in cauſes of leſſe price or moment, for dailie experience ſheweth, that the frequent vſe of thinges reuerent (ſuch is the corruption of our nature) cauſeth them to be of none accompt. Furthermore, they ought to be well adviſed that they require it not of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſuſpected faith or credite; or of perſons defamed in life and conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation. For an oath offered to ſuch (without greater neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie)
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:13213:5"/>argueth a lightnes and want of good diſcretion in the Magiſtrate, who thereby wittinglie doeth miniſter an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of perjurie, whiche if it followe, howe great is the fault? Moreouer, that they charge no man by oath to doe the thing impoſſible or beyonde his power. For <hi>impoſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium nulla est obligatio,</hi> nor any thing that is vnlawfull, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conuenient, or vngodlie. Neither force any man to ſweare raſhlie or vnaduiſedlie. For if the vaine and inconſiderate ſwearer ſhall nor be vnpuniſhed, howe ſhall the procurer eſcape Gods vengeance? That they abuſe not the ſimpli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie of the Deponent by intricate, captious, or ſubtill que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions:
<note place="margin">1. Theſ. ca. 4</note> for let no man (ſayeth the holy Apoſtle Saint Paul) beguile or craftelie circumuent his brother, for the Lorde is an auenger of all ſuch things. Finallie in the miniſtring of an oath the Magiſtrates ought to reſpect all thoſe things which the partie depoſing ought to haue before his eyes, that is the glorie of God, the maintenance of trueth, &amp; the good of our brethren.</p>
               <p>Theſe things graunted, which cannot be denied, it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequentlie followeth that the forcing of Oathes by Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naries and Iudges Eccleſiaſticall generallie to anſwere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all ſuch queſtions or interrogatories as they ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde or miniſter touching eyther the thoughts, wordes or deedes of him that is to depoſe, is contrarie to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable inſtitution, lawfull vſe, and true ende of an oathe. And that whoſoeuer by coulour of authoritie, threatning ſpeaches, dureſſe of impriſonment, or other paine co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth any man to ſweare in ſuch maner, doeth highlie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende againſt th'inviolable rules before remembred.</p>
               <p>For firſt as it hath bene ſaide, the ordeyning and inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an oath was to helpe and relieue the neceſſitie of men in the cauſes before rehearſed. But there is no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie or vigent cauſe why ſuch a general oath ſhould either be required or take, ſince the ſame is neither for aſſurance of duetie, couenaunt, contract or promiſe, neyther yet for confirmation of trueth in any cauſe or matter of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie. If it bee alleadged that the ſame is requiſite for the enquiring and finding out of ſuſpected faultes, whereof
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:13213:6"/>there is no proofe, and to ſearch and trie the euill mindes and corrupt conſciences of daungerous diſſemblers, and ſo neceſſarie for the gouernement both of the Church and common wealth. By this allegation firſt all ſuch are juſtly reproued, who hauing practiſed and put in ure this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall oath, where otherwiſe there was ſufficiencie of proofe. And yet thereby nothing is ſaide for the maintenance of their doings in that behalfe, ſince by the like reaſon there ſhould be erected a Court of Inquiſition more then Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh to ſifte &amp; ranſacke by oath the moſt ſecret thoughtes and conſciences of all men in generall, enforcing them ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to accuſe them ſelues (not as in the Papiſticall ſhrift; where ſecrecie was enjoyned) to their publique ſhame, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and condemnation, or els for the auoyding of ſuch miſchiefe and inconuenience, to committe moſt wilfull and damnable perjurie. But as this I ſuppoſe in all good mens opinions, were intollerable, ſo of the other I aſſure my ſelfe there can be no ſounde rule, ſufficient preſident or example alleadged: Except peraduenture the proceding of the high Prieſt, the Scribes and Elders of the Iewes in their Conſiſtorie againſt our Sauiour Chriſt, ſhall be vou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched and mainteined for a ſufficient preſident in that bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, who maliciouſlie appoſing and examining him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his doctrine (although not by oath) would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie haue pickt out and drawne from him ſelfe ſome mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of accuſation, whereby to haue condemned him. But the aunſwere and authoritie of Chriſt (I doubt not) wilbe allowed among Chriſtians, both for ſounde and ſufficient to refell and condemne the practize of thoſe malignaunt Prieſtes, who knowing their ſubtill purpoſe and intent, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred them to his auditours, and beeing injuſtlie ſtriken, replied: If I haue euill ſpoken, beare witneſſe of the euill, but if I haue well ſpoken, why ſmiteſt thou mee, juſtifying hereby his former aunſwere, and forcing therewithall his aduerſaries to ſeeke for witneſſes to teſtifie againſt him.</p>
               <p>The true vſe and ende of an oth is, as aforeſaide, That due honor may be giuen vnto God, the trueth confirmed, Iuſtice maintained, innocencie protected, and an end had
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:13213:6"/>of ſtrife and contention. But how is God glorified hereby, or not rather diſhonored, when as his ſacred inſtitution is ſo greatlie peruerted, and an oath forced to an other courſe and purpoſe, then he in his diuine wiſedome hath appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as by that which hath and ſhalbe ſpoken, doth &amp; ſhall manifeſtlie appeare. The trueth in controuerſie is not ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by confirmed, ſince there is no iſſue ioined in this caſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene parties affirming and denying, and how can iuſtice by ſuch an oath be maintained, when as the cauſe for which the oath is vrged, ſtandeth not in lawfull courſe of judgment? for as it is well ſaid of a learned man:
<note place="margin">Bracton.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudicium est in qualibet actione trinus actus trium perſonarum: Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis, actoris, &amp; rei, ſecundum quod large accipi poſſunt huinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modi perſonae, quod duae ſunt ad minus inter quos vertatur co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tentio, &amp; tertia perſona ad minus qui iudicet, alioquin no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> erit iudicium, cum istae perſonae ſunt partes principales in iudicio, fine quibus iudicium conſistere non potest.</hi> Then whenſoeuer any fault or matter of offence by meanes of this kinde of compulſary oath happeneth to be diſcloſed, either we muſt ſay that the Iudge, who impoſeth the oath, is him ſelfe againſt all order of juſtice, the partie accuſer,
<note place="margin">8. H. 6. fol. 18. 5. Reg. Eli.</note> and ſo both Iudge and Promoter, which all good lawes forbidde: Or els the Deponent muſt of neceſſitie ſuſteine two princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall partes in judgement, that is to be both <hi>Actor</hi> &amp; <hi>Reus,</hi> Accuſor and accuſed, whereby the three principall parties, by the rule aforeſaide, faylinge true judgement, by no meanes may conſiſt. Furthermore, by this kinde of oath it can not be truely ſaide, that Innocentes circumuented by fraude or practiſe, are cleared, ſince there is no complaint or accuſation judiciallie exhibited. Except we ſhall affirme that the Iudge or Magiſtrate by enforcing ſuch an oathe, doeth him ſelfe play the patt of a ſubtil circumventor and accuſor, which as it is a moſt wicked ſinne in any man, ſo in the perſon of a publique Magiſtrate (whoſe actions ſhould be ſincere) the ſame is moſt deteſtable. And finally, howe can an ende of controuerſie enſue by ſuch an oathe, whereas no quarrell or complaint is any way dependinge. Nay rather the ſame is often tymes the cauſe of ſtirring vp
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13213:7"/>of debate and contention in ſteade of former quietnes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing principallie vſed not to make an end of controuerſies, but to procure ſome accuſation, and that by the ſecrete malice of ſome vndermining or malignant aduerſarie or calumniatour.</p>
               <p>Againe, ſince an oath is to be taken in judgement, that is with good aduiſement and conſideration of the matter, wherein the Deponent is to call the Name of God to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and that whoſoeuer otherwiſe taketh an oath, doeth therein vainelie and indiſcreetlie abuſe the Name of God. Howe can this generall oath be eyther rightlie vrged or receyued without great offence to his diuine Maieſtie, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as the partie depoſing is not before he ſwear, made acquainted nor vnderſtandeth what queſtions or interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatories ſhal be demau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded, but by his oath hath faſt bound and ſubjected him ſelfe to the diſcretion or indiſcretion of another, that is the Iudge Eccleſiaſticall, who hauinge ſtraightlie tied and ſnared this ſeelie ſubiect, may nowe vſe or abuſe him at his will and pleaſure, eyther againſt lawe enforcing him by the bande of his oath to accuſe him ſelfe euen of his moſt ſecret and inward thoughtes, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to chriſtian charitie, yea humanitie it ſelfe, conſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him to enforme againſt his naturall parentes, deareſt friends, and neareſt neighbors, or to bewray with griefe of heart ſuch matters of ſecrecie, as otherwiſe were inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient &amp; peraduenture not honeſt to be reuealed. In which hard proceeding beſides the great hazard &amp; peril of wilful perjurie without all neceſſitie of an oath, great trouble of minde and ſcruple of conſcience muſt needes enſue, when as the Deponent on the one ſide, conſidering the waight &amp; heauie burthen of his oath, feareth to conceale any thing: and on the other ſide finding him felfe thereby entrapped, ſhrinketh to make aunſwere to the queſtions propounded. Whereof you may beholde a moſt miſerable and lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſpectacle in the booke of Actes &amp; monumentes, where in a large table is ſet forth the great iniquitie and rigorous dealing of <hi>Longland</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> in the time of the late Prince of famous memorie, King H. the eight. Which
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:13213:7"/>bloudie Biſhop by forced and violent oathes and captious interrogatories, conſtrayned the children to accuſe their parentes, the parentes their naturall children, the wife her huſbande, the huſbande his wife, one brother and ſiſter an other, ſome of theſe ſeelie ſoules of ſworne becomminge forſworne, whyle they made daintie to accuſe ſuch as they dearlie affected. Of which blinde ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce (or rather mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous mindes) and intollerable iniquitie of Romiſh Biſh. and barbarous abuſe of an oath, that godlie man of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie memorie Maiſter <hi>Iohn Foxe</hi> juſtlie complaineth. For what might be added more to extreame crueltie, ſaue only this one point of deteſtable inhumanitie (whiche alſo was purſuaunt as a part of that tragical church-gouernement) to compell the children to ſet fire to their condemned pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentes. Which example of crueltie ſayeth that good man, as it is contrarie both to God and nature, ſo hath it not bene ſeene or heard of in the memorie of the heathen.</p>
               <p>That wicked king <hi>Herode</hi> (as it is recorded by the holy Euangeliſtes Mathewe and Marke) voluntarilie promiſed, and that with an oath, to giue the dauncing daughter of <hi>Herodias</hi> his harlot, whatſoeuer ſhee ſhould demaunde. As this vnaduiſed oath proceeding of vaine pleaſure and delight vppon the wicked demaunde of that Damoſell wrought much griefe of minde in the king, ſo was it the cauſe of the ſudden diſpatche and murther of that iuſt man Iohn the Baptiſt. And although it may truelie be ſaid that Herode was not bounde by his oath to haue accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed ſo foule and wicked a deede, yet can it not bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied but that the ſame was a raſhe and inconſiderate oath, and ſo an offence againſt the Maieſtie of Almightie God. And what difference is there I pray you betweene the oath of <hi>Herode</hi> and that which nowe we haue in queſtion, the one being to performe or graunt whatſoeuer ſhould be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired: and the other, to aunſwere to all queſtions that ſhalbe demaunded, ſince there may be as vnlawfull and as vnhoneſt queſtions miniſtred, as vngodlie requeſtes made or deſired.</p>
               <p>Againe, it would not be forgotten that in all the volume
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:13213:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:13213:8"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:13213:9"/>the ſacred ſcriptures (to my remembrance) there is no one preſident or example to bee ſhewed of any ſuch generall oath taken by any godlie man in priuate, or exacted by any Magiſtrate in publique, neither yet any rule, lawe, or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement for the ſame.</p>
               <p>But againſt this our laſt aſſertion may happilie bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadged by ſome fauourer of this foule abuſe, the manner of triall by adjuration of the ſuſpected wife, that is the law of jelouſie. The inquiſition and expiation of man-ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, where the authour is vnknowen, and the examination of <hi>Achan:</hi> all which neuertheleſſe make nothing for theſe generall oathes, or thoſe enjoyned <hi>ex officio,</hi> as by the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the lawes and hiſtorie it ſelfe ſhall eaſilie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. For as concerning the lawe of jelouſie, although the wife were to be tried by oath and adjuration in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner and with thoſe circumſtances as is there preſcribed, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſatisfie the reſtleſſe head of her jelous huſbande, if ſhee were guyltleſſe, or to receyue by the wonderfull workinge of that accurſed water, if ſhee were ſaultie condigne puniſhment for her heynous offence, both of perjurie and adulterie, yet is it verie manifeſt in this caſe that the wife is not ſommoned or cited by the Prieſt or Magiſtrate <hi>ex officio,</hi> but brought vnto him by her accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing huſband, who vpon offence conceyued offring vp his complaint, and thervpon the woman is called for, and put to her purgation, well knowing her accuſor, and hauinge perfect notice before ſhee ſweare of the crime objected. Moreouer, who is ſo ſimple that ſeeth not howe weake an argument or concluſion this were. God hath appointed an oath to be taken by the wife in this eſpeciall and ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar caſe of jelouſie for the ſatisfaction of the ſuſpitious minde of the huſband, <hi>Ergo</hi> euery Iudge Eccleſiaſticall to ſatisfie his jelous ſuſpition or imagination of any crime, may appoſe by oath and compell men to their purgation. For by as good reaſon the Ordinarie or Iudge Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call may alſo vpon euerie ſuch oath denounce a curſſe of conſumption and rotting to the partie depoſing in ſuch &amp; the ſame maner as there is preſcribed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:13213:9"/>
And as touchinge the inquiſition for murther or man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaughter before remembred, it is ordeyned, that the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of that Citie, which vpon meaſure taken falleth out to be next vnto the ſlayne man, ſhould waſhe their handes ouer a beheaded Heyfer, proteſting and ſaying in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Prieſtes: Our hands haue not ſhed this bloud, neyther haue our eyes ſeene the ſlear. O Lorde be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full vnto thy people Iſrael, whom thou haſt redeemed, &amp; lay no innocent bloud to the charge of this people, &amp;c. Howe any thing here may proue the exacting of oathes to be lawfull, I ſee not. A man is ſlayne, th'offendour vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen, th'Elders by this eſpeciall lawe of expiation doe proteſt as aforeſaide. But where is an oath in this caſe gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to any particular perſon? If this proteſtation ſhall bee thought in ſome ſorte to conteruaile an oath of purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yet where is there any proteſtation or oath required or taken to aunſwere generallie to ſuch Interrogatories as ſhalbe propounded vpon vnknowne, ſecret, or barelie ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpected matter? Nay we ſee euidentlie, the fact and felonie (to th'offence both of God and man) to bee publique and apparaunt, th'offendor only lyeth hidden and vnknowne. On the contrarie, thoſe Inquiſitors <hi>ex officio,</hi> haue the man before them whom they will examine, but the matter for the moſt part is ſecreat and concealed which they enquire after, and many tymes there is no matter at all but bare &amp; naked ſuſpition or fame of a cry me neuer committed.</p>
               <p>Concerning <hi>Achan</hi> and the proceeding againſt him, we ſee by the ſacred hiſtorie howe the offence in generall is by God him ſelfe made manifeſt vnto <hi>Joſhua</hi> the Prince of the people (vz) That an excommunicate or curſed thing was taken and concealed, &amp;c. th'offendour was onely to be founde out. Inquiſition being had by lot or otherwiſe, (God aſſiſting) <hi>Achan</hi> is deprehended as guiltie. What followed? He is by <hi>Ioſua</hi> examined of the particular, vſing theſe wordes: My ſonne, I beſeeche thee giue glorie to the Lord God of Iſraell, and make confeſſion vnto him, and ſhewe me nowe what thou haſt done, hide it not from me. Herevpon the detected <hi>Achan</hi> confeſſeth the trueth in
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:13213:10"/>particular. But where doeth it appeare that hee was depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, or by what conceyued wordes or forme of oath doeth he ſweare? Except wee ſhall ſay, there is no difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the intreatie or charge of the Magiſtrate, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring the glorie of God, and an oath taken and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by th'offendour to confeſſe the trueth. Which graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, it muſt conſequentlie followe, that whoſoeuer is in that manner charged and confeſſeth not the trueth, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he haue no will to ſweare, is both a liar and a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon perjured, which were a harde concluſion. Nay rather ſuch kinde of charge as <hi>adiuro te,</hi> as a learned man ſayeth. <hi>Non est alium ad iurandum inducere,
<note place="margin">Thomas Aquinas</note> ſed per ſimilitu dinem juramenti alium ad aliud age<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum inducere.</hi> And ſuch ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are alſo vſed for commaundementes in the name of the Diuine Maieſtie,
<note place="margin">Act. cap. 19.1. Theſ. ca. 5</note> as we reade done by the Exorciſtes, &amp; by Sain Paule, who chargeth the Theſſal. in the Lord, that his Epiſtle be read vnto all the brethren the Saints. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if euerie ſuch kinde of ſpeache ſhould ſtraight way make an oath, then would it followe (wdich were abſurde) that the Deuill made our Sauiour to ſweare at ſuch time as he ſaide, I charge thee by God, that thou torment mee not.</p>
               <p>I knowe very well what that learned and excellent light of Gods Church Maiſter <hi>Caluin</hi> ſaith in his booke of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of chriſtian Religion, That is, howe <hi>Joſua</hi> min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to driue <hi>Achan</hi> to confeſſe the trueth, ſaid: My ſonne giue glorie to the Lord God of Iſraell, meaning thereby that the Lord is grieuouſlie diſhonored, if a man ſweare falſlie by him. And this maner of ſpeach ſayeth hee, was vſed amonge the Iewes, ſo oft as any was called to take an oath, as appeareth by the like proteſtation that the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees vſe in the Goſpell of Saint Iohn. In the booke alſo of <hi>Ezra</hi> we reade the ſame phraſe (Giue prayſe vnto the Lorde) as ſome in Engliſhe haue tranſlated it,
<note place="margin">Cap. 9.</note> but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Latine tranſlation of the learned <hi>Tremelius</hi> &amp; <hi>Iunius,</hi> the wordes are, <hi>aedite confeſſionem Jehouae Deo.</hi> So that although it bee graunted that where an oath was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen for the confeſſion of the trueth, there the Magiſtrate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:13213:10"/>vſed thoſe wordes (Giue glorie vnto God, putting the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie in minde thereby of the Maieſtie of Almightie God) yet followeth it not that in euerie place where wee finde the ſame ſpeach, there the partie to whom it was ſpoken, had taken an oath to confeſſe the matter whereof hee was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded. But be it graunted that <hi>Achan</hi> made his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion by oath, yet nothing will enſue thereof to juſtifie the dealings of thoſe Inquiſitors <hi>ex officio.</hi> For if thoſe rough and rigorous exactors of an oath followinge onely this legall courſe of inquiſition ſet forth in this ſacred hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie, That is after an offence committed ſo grieuous and daungerous to the publique eſtate, and the ſame made knowen and notorious, would then onelie ſeeke out the partie offending, and that by due and lawfull courſe of tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: and hauing founde him, then after ſo mylde and cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous a manner, and in the name of God intreat, or (if they thinke good) depoſe him to reueale the trueth in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar: No man (I ſuppoſe) would finde him ſelf grieued with their proceedings. But this their vnjuſt dealinge in this great abuſe of an oath, can not by authoritie of the holie ſcriptures be any way defended or mainteyned. Wiſelie therefore and with good diſcretion did that godlie man <hi>William Thorp</hi> in the time of King Henry the fourth,
<note place="margin">William Thorp.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willed by that bloodie perſecutor of the true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans Archb. <hi>Arundell,</hi> to lay his hande vpon the booke, and ſweare faithfullie to ſubmit him ſelfe to his correction, &amp; to ſtande vnto and fulfill his ordinaunce, deſired firſte to knowe, wherefore he ſhould be corrected, and vnto what ordinaunce he was to be obliged, which being declared to this effect, that he ſhould forſake all the opinions of the ſectes of <hi>Lollardes</hi> (in deede the true Chriſtians) that hee ſhould preache no more vnto the people, &amp; that he ſhould from thenceforth become an accuſor of ſuch as him ſelfe was. He vtterlie refuſed to take any ſuch oath, leaſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he ſhould haue fallen into many foule and heynous ſinnes and offences againſt God, as the abjuringe of true Religion, the forſaking of his lawfull calling againſt his conſcience, &amp; to his publique reproach to become a bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:13213:11"/>accuſor, or (as he him ſelfe ſayth) an appeallor of his brethren, euerie Biſhops eſpie, and the ſomner of all Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lande, deepely deteſting ſuch a bad office, as vnméete for a Miniſter of the word: nay altogither vnbeſeeming a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Chriſtian, If any man will ſay as this Archbiſh. that a ſubject ought not to ſuppoſe that his Prelat will co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund him any vnlawfull thing, but ſhould repoſe him ſelf in the good diſcretion &amp; vpright dealing of his ordinarie, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further aunſwere: Let the ſubtill practiſe of this one Prelate, and the cruell and the accurſed dealinges of that barbarous Bi. <hi>Longlande</hi> ſtande at this preſent for a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient caueat to euerie man that ſhall depoſe, to take heede howe he giue ouer-much credite to ſuch gloſinge and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyuable ſpeaches, leaſt too late he finde it true, that <hi>faire wordes make fooles faine.</hi> Neythet is this any ſufficient al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legation to ſay, that the partie Deponent is no further bounde to aunſwere then the lawe requireth, howe gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall ſoeuer his oath be, ſince it is falſe, for the conſcience of ſuch a Deponent to ſtande vpon termes and queſtions, howe farre by lawe, and by what lawe he is bounde to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere.</p>
               <p>Will you heare alſo what that godlie and bleſſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Maiſter <hi>Iohn Lambert</hi> ſayth concerning the Exactinge of ſuch kinde of oathes,
<note place="margin">Iohn Lam bert.</note> after he had acknowledged it law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full at the commaundement of a Iudge to take an oathe, to ſay the trueth, wiſhing the Magiſtrates neuertheles to miniſter oathes with great diſcretion &amp; good aduiſement, and exhorting them to forbeare and ſpare them in trifling cauſes and matters of no neceſſitie, leaſt by too much haunt, firſt contempt, than perjurie, doe creepe in. Hee proceedeth further to this effect. This haue I ſhewed ſaith he, becauſe it pitieth me to heare and ſee the contrarie vſed in ſome of our Nation, and ſuch alſo as name them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſpirituall men, and ſhould be head miniſters of the Church, who incontinentlie as any man commeth before them, anon they call for a booke, and doe mooue him to ſweare without any futher reſpite, yea and they will charg him by vertu of the contentes of the Euangely, to make
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:13213:11"/>true relation of all they ſhal demaunde him, he not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what they will demaunde, neither whether it bee law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to ſhewe them the trueth of their demaunde or no, for ſuch things there be that are not lawfull to bee ſhewed. As if I were accuſed of fornication, and none could be founde in mee, or if they ſhould require me to ſweare to bewraye another that I haue knowen to offende in that vice, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it were expedient to holde me ſtill and not to followe their will, for it ſhould be contrarie to charitie, if I ſhould ſo aſſent to bewray them that I neede not, and to whom perhaps (though I haue knowne them to offende, yet tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of their amendment) I haue promiſed afore to keepe their fault ſecrete. Yea moreouer ſuch Iudges ſometimes not knowing by any due proofe, that ſuch as haue to doe before them are culpable, will enforce them by an oath to detect them ſelues in opening before them their heartes. In this ſo doing I cannot ſee that men need to condeſcend in their requeſtes: for as it is in the lawe, <hi>Nemo tenetur pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere ſcipſum.</hi> And in another place of the lawe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: <hi>Cogitationis poenam nemo patiatur.</hi> To this agreeth the common prouerbe, <hi>Cogitationes liberae ſunt à vectigalibus,</hi> Thoughtes be free from toll. By which wiſe ſpeach of this good man we may ſee condemned, and that for juſt cauſe and vpon ſounde reaſons th'indiſcreete and vnlawfull en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forcing of this kinde of oathe, ſeruing to no good, nay ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bad endes &amp; purpoſes. We read alſo howe <hi>Bonner</hi> that infamous bloudſucker, vnworthie the name of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe, hunting (as the woolfe for his pray) after matter of accuſation, among many other his miſchieuous and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable factes, offered alſo this oath <hi>ex officio</hi> vnto the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe priſoners of that holy and worthie Martyr Maiſter <hi>Philpot,</hi> ſaying after the raſhe and indiſcrete maner before remembred, Holde them a booke, you ſhall ſweare by the contentes of that booke, that you ſhall (all maner of affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion laide a part) ſay the trueth of all ſuch articles as you ſhalbe demaunded co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning this man here preſent (mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Maiſter <hi>Philpot.</hi>) But thoſe wiſe and godlie priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, well knowing and conſidering howe they ought to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:13213:12"/>take an oath, aunſwered to this vnjuſt requeſt: That they would not ſweare, except they firſt knewe where vnto, and being therevpon offred an oath, and that with threates of Excommunication to aunſwere the articles propounded againſt themſelues, refuſed it alſo, ſaying: That they would not accuſe them ſelues. So that wee ſee plainely by theſe examples, as alſo by that auncient and godlie writing inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled <hi>The prayer and complaint of the Ploughman,</hi> that this kinde of generall oath and examinations <hi>ex officio mero,</hi> were not firſt miſhked by Ieſuites and ſeminarie Prieſtes, and fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them deriued to others that miſlike gouernement and would bring the Church to an Anarchie, as the world hath bene borne in hande. But by true Chriſtians, holie, learned and Religious men, and that for good cauſes and conſiderations why they ſhould ſo doe.</p>
               <p>And I ſhould much meruaile, were it not that the world hath euer bene ſet in wickednes, howe any that profeſſe the holie name and title of Chriſtianitie, durſt at any time put in practize within this Realme or elſwhere, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane and more then heatheniſhe manner of Inquiſition, not onely repugnaunt to God and Chriſtian Religion, but contrarie alſo to the rules and cannons of the Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian church of Rome. Which lawes (if I be not deceyued) are more juſt and leſſe vnjuſt a great deale, then ſuch as haue taken vpon them to judge by coulor of the ſame. So that in a ſorte it may be verified of them which was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpoken of the people of <hi>Athens,</hi> that hauing juſt &amp; good lawes, they neuertheleſſe behaued them ſelues as bad and diſhoneſt men. For it is ſaide by ſome of their Canoniſtes,
<note place="margin">Canonists</note> 
                  <hi>Procedere ex officio mero, est quando Iudex à ſeipſo &amp; ex officio aſſumit informationes contra delinquen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem, &amp; contra eum procedit, &amp; hoc est quod dicitur procede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re per viam inquiſitionis. Et recte loquendo, inquirere contra aliquem,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ul. Cla. in proe. crim. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> fin. 3. quaeſt. verſ. quaero quibu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> non est ei tranſferre Inquiſitionem, ſed recipere te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes ſeu informationes contra eum.</hi> And moreouer, <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare inquiſitionem contra aliquem, est facere proceſſum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formatiuum aſſumendo informationes &amp; iudicia contra eum ſuper alique delicto.</hi> So that to proceede by inquiſition, is
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:13213:12"/>not to make the partie by oath or examination to bee his owne accuſor, but to accept and receyue information and witneſſes againſt him.</p>
               <p>And in what ſorte and maner the proceeding ought to be, is alſo declared to this effect: <hi>Iudex nunquam debet procedere ex officio, &amp; ſic per viam inquiſitionis, niſi aliquod precedat quod appareat viam inquiſitioni ſcilicet, vel defa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matio, vel quaerela partis, vel denunciatio, vel huiufmodi, ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liter proceſſus erit, nullus ipſo jure neque in hoc intenduntur notificationes factae extra judicialiter, neque illae quae fiunt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certo autore, &amp; ſuppreſſo nomine notificantis.</hi> By whiche wordes manifeſtlie appeareth, that no Iudge Eccleſiaſticall ought to proceede by way of inquiſition, except there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede a defamation of the partie complaint, or informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt him, intelligence of faultes and offences out of courſe of judgement, or by vncertaine authour, or ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed name, is wholie by the Lawe rejected, but by the executors thereof altogither admitted.</p>
               <p>Another alſo therevnto agreeing, ſayth:
<note place="margin">Io. pet. de ferr. in prae. ſub rubr. form. inqui ſitionis &amp; fama publ.</note> That the inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition is not orderlie done, but where <hi>infamia praecedat, vel talia judicia ſufficientia quae probentur per testes idoneos.</hi> And to prooue the fame or infamie, there is required <hi>teſtes multi,</hi> the reaſon, <hi>quia dicta paucorum non infamant.</hi> Secondlie, they muſt bee <hi>graues &amp; honesti, non male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoli, nec inimici partis.</hi> Thirdlie, they muſt bee ſuch as are conuerſant in the place where the partie hath liued, whereby they may bee acquainted with the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and manner of his life and conuerſation, wherevppon chiefelie riſeth the true judgement of his good or euill fame. Fourthlie, thoſe witneſſes ought to be receyued ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciallie. Fiftlie, they muſt be depoſed. And ſixtlie, they are to render a wife and ſufficient cauſe of their knowledge of the infamie. The Iudge in no cauſe (if he would of his owne knowledge ſay, the partie is infamous) is to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued or beleeued, the reaſon is, for that the lawe will <hi>quod ſecundum acta &amp; probata justitia ministretur.</hi> And the grounde and foundation of the inquiſition muſt not be extorted or wreſted from the partie, but, lawfullie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:13213:13"/>as aforeſaide by ſufficient witneſſes. Notwithſtanding all which lawes, what contrarie courſes haue bene practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed by Ordinaries and Cleargie men, many haue felt, and euery man knoweth too well. So that concerninge their judiciall Courtes and Conſiſtories, the ſaying of the Poet is verified, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icta iacet pietas, &amp; virgo caede madentes vlti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma coelestium terras astraea reliquit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But ſince that more then two quaternions of learned Canoniſtes haue of late taken the paines to ſet downe the vndoubted groundes of the lawe Eccleſiaſticall (as they ſay) according to which the proceedings haue bene vſed time out of minde, in all the Courtes Eccleſiaſticall of this Realme, and all other proceedings haue bene at all times reformable by appellations, Let vs heare alſo what they ſay concerning this matter.</p>
               <p>Theſe Doctors firſte graunt it to bee good and ſounde law, That no man may be vrged to bewray him ſelf in hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den and ſecrete crimes, or ſimplie therein to accuſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. They confeſſe further, that if any man beſides the Ordinarie will proſequute in their Courtes, making him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe partie to proue a cryme whereof there is ſuſpition: The partie conuented in that caſe, albeit he muſt anſwere on his oath to other articles not principallie touching the verie crime objected, is not bounde by lawe to aunſwere vpon oath any articles of the verie crime it ſelfe. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe ſay they, when by circumſtaunces once knowne a broade, ſecrete crymes are become vehementlie to bee ſuſpected, and offenſiue to the well diſpoſed, and daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be ſuffred, then are they meete by enquirie and all good meanes to bee diſcouered, to the ende they may bee reformed, &amp; the partie delinquent brought to penitencie, and others diſcouraged to commit the like.</p>
               <p>The wayes and meanes how ſuſpition &amp; fame of crimes come to the Ordinaries eares, they ſaye are theſe, manie bruites of credible perſons called in the lawe <hi>clamoſa infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuatio,</hi> and preſentmentes of Church-wardens and Syde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men: which preſentmentes if they be not direct thorough ignoraunce of the preſentours or inſufficient in the lawe
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:13213:13"/>to proue a fame (yet ſome ſcandall therevppon growinge) howe litle by like is not reſpected, th'Ordinarie by lawe Eccleſiaſticall and good diſcretion may examine other witneſſes, being neighbours, warning the partie ſuſpected to be preſent. The fame once prooued (ſay they) or the firſt preſentement ſufficient than th'ordinarie of duetie, &amp; for the publique truſt repoſed in him is, to proceede a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the infamed, although no other man will, which by lawe is termed proceeding by enquirie, eſpeciall <hi>ex officie,</hi> they adde a reaſon for confirmation <hi>Ne maleficia remano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant impunita, vtque Prouincia purgetur malis hominibus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And in this ſorte, if the Ordinarie proceed <hi>ex officio,</hi> and the partie denie the crime objected, then by lawe hee is enjoyned his purgation. At which time of purgation (ſay they) he muſt directlie aunſwere in clearing or conuincing him ſelfe <hi>de veritate vel falſitate ipſius criminis objecti,</hi> and his compurgators are to ſweare <hi>de credulitate</hi> (weying his feare of God and conuerſation of former tymes) That they beleeue he hath taken a true oath, whiche if they all doe, then he is holden cleare or diſmiſſed. But if he fayle in his purgation, then <hi>fictione juris</hi> hee is taken to bee guiltie and to be reformed.</p>
               <p>They ſhewe likewiſe a reaſon of diuerſitie betweene the proceeding in the caſe <hi>ex officio,</hi> And that which is by ſuite of the partie, That is, <hi>Licet nemo tenetur ſeipſum prodere, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men proditus per famam tenetur ſeipſum ostendere vtrum poſſit ſuam innocentiam ostendere, &amp; ſeipſum purgare.</hi> And a reaſon of that reaſon is added, becauſe penaunces enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the ordinarie, are not taken in lawe to be <hi>poenae</hi> but <hi>medicinae,</hi> or tending to the reformation of the delinquent. Th'example of others and ſatisfaction of the Church of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended: And ſo they conclude vpon all their reaſons, that the ſuſpected are not to make ſcruple to diſcouer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues after fame.</p>
               <p>This being the true and onely courſe of proceeding by Ordinaries and Eccleſiaſticall Iudges in cauſes criminall, where is then become the exacting of thoſe general oathes ſo often vſed to aunſwere all Interrogatories that ſhalbee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:13213:14"/>miniſtred, and that before notice or vnderſtanding (for the moſt parte) of the cryme objected. And the extortinge by oath of the ground and foundation of the inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the partie conuented, doeth it not appeare by the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of theſe learned men, that the ſame haue no good or ſufficient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> by the lawe, howe long or much ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer by cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>t &amp; pretence of lawe and juſtice they haue bin practized or impoſed.</p>
               <p>And as concerning their proceedings <hi>exofficio</hi> to forced p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gations approued (as they ſeeme to affirme) both by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Eccleſiaſticall and tytle of preſcription, if we looke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thereto, and take good view thereof, what other thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>all we finde then harde and vnjuſt dealing towards men, and great abuſe of the Name and Maicſtie of Almightie God, cloaked and ſhadowed neuertheleſſe vnder the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and painted gloſſes of beautifullſhewes and feyned pretences of purging of Prouinces, Reformation of delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentes neceſſarie examples, diſcharge of publique truſt, and ſatisfaction of the offended church, honeſt and hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable termes in deede, but ill applied to this purpoſe.</p>
               <p>For firſte, as concerning the injuſtice offred vnto men, if it be a true and ſounde principle or Maxime in lawe, not denied by themſelues, That <hi>Nemo tenetur ſeipſum prode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> where ſhould the benefite thereof be had or taken but in their Courtes and Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſtories. But if it ſhould be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that this rule faileth where a man is <hi>proditus per fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam,</hi> doeth not that as a gloaſe confoundinge the text wholie and altogither deſtroy that rule or principle, except for ſome reliefe this narrowe ſhifte may be vſed. That the fame neuertheleſſe ſtandeth in force where any other then the Ordinarie aſſumeth to proue that cryme.</p>
               <p>But in this caſe alſo they haue ſo weakned this maxime, that ſcarcelie will it ſtande for a minome, affirminge (if I miſtake them not) that the infamed muſt aunſwere on his oath to other articles not principallie touching the verie crymes objected. For what ſhould be meant by other ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles but ſuch as concerne circumſtaunces and induce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes to the cryme, And is not this to goe like the crabb
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13213:14"/>oblique, and to proceede the ſame way, although not to treade the direct ſteppes? But why there ſhould bee any diſtaunce betweene the ſuyte or inſtance of the partie and the proceeding <hi>ex officio,</hi> I knowe not the reaſon. Allead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged therefore is this, Penaunces enjoyned by Ordinaries are not taken to bee <hi>panae</hi> but <hi>medicinae,</hi> what their lawe preſumeth is not ſufficient reaſon to prooue their lawe reaſonable, but what they are in deed is to be weyed. And ſhall they be medicines onelie, where proceeding is <hi>ex of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio?</hi> Or tende they in that caſe alone to the reformation of the delinquent, Th'example of others, and ſatisfaction of the Church? May not all this aſwell bee verefied where the cryme is complained of, and puniſhed at th'inſtaunce of the partie? And ſhall not penaunce although it bee but the ſtanding in a ſheete, as well as the ſtanding on the pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorie, reſpect of publique ſhame and reproache (grieuous and odious vnto all men) be accompted for a puniſhment? True it is, all corrections are or ſhould bee medicines for the amendement of maners. But doeth it therefore follow that the ſame be no paines or puniſhments?</p>
               <p>As concerning th'offence to God by the abuſe of his Name and Maieſtie, Haue we not learned before that to offer an oath vnto perſons defamed in life and conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſpeciallie concerning the matter of his owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt life argueth a lightnes and wante of good diſcretion in the Magiſtrate, who thereby wittinglie doeth miniſter an occaſion of perjurie? And are not all thoſe on whome theſe purgations are impoſed, men greatlie defamed, and vehementlie ſuſpected of the crymes objected, for as theſe Doctours affirme the law when ſecrete crymes by circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunces knowne abroade, are become vehementlie ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, offenſiue and daungerous, then are they firſte enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of. The proceeding alſo by inquiſition beginning vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon fame, proued not ſlenderlie, but by preſentment vpon oath, or by depoſed witneſſes, being many honeſt, voide of malice, neighbours to the partie, and rendring a wiſe &amp; ſufficient reaſon of their knowledge concerning the ſame, And howe then may a Iudge in ſuch a caſe with any good
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:13213:15"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience to Godward, or to the ſatisfaction of his church, force an oath vpon ſuch a one for the finall ende of the cauſe? Is not the perill and preſumption of perjurie very great and pregnaunt? Knowe we not that all, or the moſte part of men liking the counſell <hi>(dedecus magis quam peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum vites)</hi> will rather hazard their ſoules then put their bodies to ſhame and reproach: preſume the lawe neuer ſo much that after fame they ſhould not make ſcruple to diſcouer them ſelues. If the like courſe of purgatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be vſed at the common lawe vpon Indightmentes of fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonie, or other criminall cauſes, what doubt were to bee made, but that perjurie in ſhort time would ouerflowe the whole lande: and ſhall we not thinke, that the ſame is not frequent in theſe kindes of purgations? But ſay they, the partie is not truſted alone, he bringeth with him his many compurgators, who depoſe alſo <hi>de credulitate,</hi> waying his feare of God and former conuerſation. Be it ſo, the matter thereby is no whit amended, but rather made worſe and impaired. For what doe thoſe compurgators but by len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their oathes, juſtifie in effect him to be honeſt, whom fame and the former deponentes haue proued to be diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and verie neare (the circumſtances conſidered) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced of the crime objected. Why rather doe not theſe Ordinaries which challendge and aſſume to them ſelues the goodlie name and tytle of ſpiritual men, if they reſpect the honor of God, and regard the ſoules of men, free the people from theſe pernitious oathes and deadlie purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and proceede to their ſentence of condemnation, not by feyned offices and fictions of lawe; but by good proofe and lawfull witneſſes? And againe, abſolue the partie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famed, where ſuch ſufficient proofe doeth faile them, why ſhould they thinke much to offer to the laitie in their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Courts, the like good meaſure, and vpright &amp; ſincere juſtice, that they themſelues finde &amp; obteine in the courts temporall of this Realme, Where neyther they nor any other are forced <hi>ex officio Iudicis,</hi> by ſtrayning oathes and ſtrong purgations, not healthfull but hurtfull to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wray or accuſe them ſelues. Perhaps this counſell would
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:13213:15"/>be receyued, if it were as profitable as good and honeſt, but according to the prouerbe <hi>auro loquente tacendum est.</hi> For it is no ſmall gaine and lucre that dailie riſeth and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creweth to the Cleargie and Courtes Eccleſiaſticall, by ſlaunder, fame, rumour, and falſe report: in reſpect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of theſe faire names of Office and diſcharge of publique duetie, are ſo cunninglie pretexed, and theſe poyſoninge purgations ſo daungerouſlie giuen for preſeruatiues. A matter being ſince well knowne vnto the worlde,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Carolus</hi> 5</note> and by the Princes of Germanie in the Counſell of <hi>Norenberg,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong many other abuſes and corruptions, moſte mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous, complained of to this effecte: It happeneth often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſay they, that men and women through ſiniſter and falſe reportes and ſlaunders, are brought before the Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall or Eccleſiaſticall Iudge, as men guiltie, and ſhall not be declared innocent before they haue cleared themſelues by an oath, which purgation ſo made, they are reſtored to their former eſtimation. And albeit the dammages and coſtes ought to bee repaide vnto ſuch as be ſo falſelie ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed, yet are the innocentes them ſelues forced to paye two Gilders and a quarter for their letters of abſolution. And this is the cauſe why the Officialls and other Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Iudges, doe ſo greatlie followe the action of ſuch vnlawfull, falſe, and ſlaunderous accuſations, challenging the hearing thereof onelie to them ſelues. Which thing no doubt (ſaye they) redowneth to the great and moſt ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar hurt and detriment of all men. For often times it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth that Women falling togither in contention through anger, hatred, or ſome other affection, doe ſpeake euill of, or ſlaunder one another, and outrage ſo much, that the one often times accuſeth the other eyther of Adulterie or Witcherie: which being brought before the Officiall, ſhee which through anger had ſo ſlaundered the other, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by an oath to excuſe and purge herſelfe, that what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer injurious or ſlaunderous worde ſhe had ſpoken, came not of any deliberate purpoſe or intent, but through wrath and diſpleaſure. In like manner th'other which is accuſed eyther of adulterie or ſorcerie, is commaunded by an oath
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:13213:16"/>to declare her innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie: ſo that it is euident vnto all men, that in ſuch caſes whether they bee guiltie or not guiltie, they muſt ſweare if they will keepe their good name and fame whereby not onely the vnlawfull lucre of gaine and money is fought, but alſo wilful perjurie forced, &amp;c. Thus theſe honorable perſons you ſee haue made it cleare what is chiefelie entended by theſe canonicall purgations, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende the Cleargie what ſoeuer they will, and howe ſuch forced oathes are not onelie offenſiue vnto God, but inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious alſo vnto men. Therefore leauing theſe men to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the fauour of gaine is ſo ſweete, togither with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous lawe, the matter which wee endeuour to prooue is, that thoſe generall oathes and oathes <hi>ex officio</hi> publiquelie heretofore much practized by Ordinaries and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Iudges, are altogither vnlawfull (whether by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall ſanctions or lawe cannon, I care not) but by the lawes of God and of this Realme. And therefore ſince we haue ſufficientlie ſpoken of the lawe of God, nowe leaſt peraduerture it may be ſaide, that ſuch Catholique oathes are warraunted by the common lawes or ſtatutes of this Realme, or by the vſe and practiſe of ſome Courtes of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, therein let vs conſider hereof alſo, and deliuer both our lawes and the Iuſtice of our land from ſo foule a ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</p>
               <p>Concerning the common lawes of this Realme, we may finde an oath diuerſlie allowed of and vſed in cauſes of ſuyte judiciallie depending. But ſuch a generall oathe or ſuch like <hi>ex officio</hi> at any time eyther offred by Magiſtrate or taken or made by ſubject of this lande, by authoritie of the common lawe, can neuer be proued, I am ſure, eyther by good recorde or ſounde reporte of the ſame. Long it were and tedious to remember the particular caſes, when and where an oath is required by the lawes and ſtatutes of this Realme. But this may be ſaide in generall, and that truelie, to the great honor and highe commendations of our gouuernement, that the ſame common lawes haue not impoſed or appointed an oathe to bee vſed otherwiſe then according to the right inſtitution thereof, &amp; the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:13213:16"/>rules before remembred: yea moreouer this may trulie be affirmed, that the common lawe of this Kingdome, yea the common wealth it ſelfe hath euer rejected and impug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a thing vnlawfull and injurious, this maner of ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, whereof we nowe intreat, as by that we ſhall hereafter ſay, may euidentlie appeare.</p>
               <p>Touching the oathes impoſed or admitted at the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon lawe by Iudges or Magiſtrates (for of them onelie we are to ſpeake.) Firſt it is vſed as by good reaſon in all Courtes of Iuſtice eſtabliſhed for determination of cauſes in ſuite or controuerſie, eyther betweene the Prince and ſubject, or the ſubjectes them ſelues, to require an oath of all ſuch as are called or produced to teſtifie their know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge concerning the matter or point in yſſue, whereby the trueth may appeare, and the cauſe receyue an ende.</p>
               <p>The defendent alſo in diuers perſonall actions volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie offring an oathe for his cleare diſcharge,
<note place="margin">Wager of lawe.</note> is admitted by courſe of the lawe therevnto, which maner of procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is termed the doing of his lawe, and ſeemeth to haue bene grounded vpon the judicialles before rehearſed, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen by God vnto his people the Iſralites, as by the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of the caſes hereafter mentioned, may be gathered. For in an action of debt brought for money due by reaſon of ſome ſimple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract, or in an action of detinue of goods and chattelles, the oath of the defendent in the one caſe, that he oweth not the money, and in the other, that hee deteineth not the things required, is allowed for a finall ende and barre vnto the pleadant. For in the former caſe the repayment of the money may be priuate and in ſecrete, &amp; ſo in the other the deliuerie of the goods. And although the baylment and deliuerie of the pleadaunt goods to the defendent were by the handes of a third perſon, or teſtified by writing, yet theſe are no cauſes to put the defendent from his oath, or wager of his lawe, for aſmuch as the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is not to the baylment or deliuerie, but to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teiner or withholding, and in the action of debt, although the defendent eyther hanging the action or otherwiſe had confeſſed the contract, yet is he to be admitted to his lawe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:13213:17"/>or oath, in ſo much as the point in ſuite is not the contract but the debt.
<note place="margin">7. H. 4. fo. 7. 9. E. 4. fo. 24</note>
               </p>
               <p>But in an action of accompt ſuppoſinge the receipt by the hands of a ſtranger or thirde perſon, the lawe is other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: for here the thing deliuered is not preciſelie in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunde, but an accompt onelie thereof required. And the receipt being the cauſe of action to which a thirde perſon is priuie as a witnes (the oath of the defendent as a thinge not of neceſſitie) is rejected. For that reaſon was the defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent put from his wager of lawe. Anno 31. Ed. 1. where the caſe was this: An action of detenewe was brought for a Challice, the defendent pleaded howe the pleadaunt deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered the ſame in gage for vj. markes, and that vppon the repayment thereof he was readie to deliuer the Challice, the pleadent replying that he had repayed the money by the handes of one ſuch, the defendent offring his oath to the contrarie, was nor admitted therevnto, inaſmuch as there was a witnes of the repayment, by whoſe teſtimonie the trueth might be knowen.</p>
               <p>And as the common lawe is thus on the part of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendent, ſo is it likewiſe for the pleadant, comminge as it were in place of a defendent. Therefore Anno 21. Ed. 3. fol. 49. the caſe was that the defendent vppon his accompt would haue diſcharged him ſelfe by certen tallyes, and ſo by his oath continued the charge againſt the defendent. But Anno 29. Ed. 3. the defendent in accompt alleadged before the Auditors, payment to the pleadant by the hands of another, and the pleadent offring his oath that hee had not teceyued the money, was in reſpect of the third perſon denied to wage his lawe. And the good diſcretion and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration which the lawe vſeth in the allowing and admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of wager of lawe, is not to be forgotten. Whiche lawe (leaſt men of light credite or doubtfull faith, ſhould take an oath) ſuffereth no man to doe his lawe, but ſuch onelie as is able to bring with him 11. other perſons of ripe yeres and of good name, to depoſe with him, that they thinke he ſweareth truelie.</p>
               <p>Neither are th'one parties or th'other in any perſonal ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:13213:17"/>by the courſes of the common lawe ſuffered to cleare themſelues by their oathes where they are charged, eyther by their lawfull writing or matter of recorde, for that theſe are teſtimonies and proofes ſufficient wherevnto faith and credite ought to be giuen, much more might bee ſaide in ſuch particulars, but theſe may ſuffice to ſhewe howe in ſuites for goods, chattels, debtes, or perſonall dueties, the common lawes of this Realme admit no ydle, vaine, ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious or vnneceſſarie oathes, neyther compell any man to ſweare concerning them, but vppon cauſe allowe of the pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and deſertes volontarie and neceſſarie oath for an ende of the controuerſie.</p>
               <p>As touching the cauſes and controuerſies for landes and inheritaunces depending in fuyte, eyther in admitting or requiring of oathes, ſome fewe caſes there be: Neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe where an oath for them is vſed, As if a <hi>Praecipe quod reddat</hi> be brought of lande wherein the tenaunt was not lawfullie ſommoned, he may vpon returne of the proces of graund cape, wage his lawe for none ſommons, and thereby (as not well executed) abate the demaundentes writ, in which caſe an oath ſeemeth rightlie to bee admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſince the cauſe is both of weight and neceſſitie to the tenaunt, this being the onely way to relieue him againſt the vntrue returne of the Sherife, whereby his lande for want of apparaunce was to bee recouered againſt him. For as the lawe ſeemeth to way a triall of this ſommons by 12. men is not allowable. And although it may bee ſaide, that the tenaunt vpon his loſſe by default might haue a writ of deceipt, and recouer againe his lande,
<note place="margin">33. H. 6. fo.</note> yet that often times falleth out to be a faint remedie, the death of ſuch as were returned ſommoners depriuing him of that aduantage. In the caſe alſo of deceipt vpon a recouerie by default, the ſommoners, viewers, and perueors, are judiciallie exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by oath, whether they haue duelie accordinge to the lawes of the lande, executed and perfourmed that whiche appertayneth vnto them, who in this caſe are vſed but as witneſſes to ſearch and ſifte out by them the good or euill dealing of the Sherife by whom the execution of the writ
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:13213:18"/>and proceſſe was committed.
<note place="margin">41. Ed. 3. fo.</note> In like maner, if the plaint. in a <hi>ſcire facias.</hi> recouer by default, &amp; the defendent bring this action of deceipt againſt the Sherife, the bailife and the partie that ſued execution of the lande, proceſſe ſhalbe awarded againſt the ſuppoſed garniſhers, and vppon their apparaunce they ſhalbe examined (and that by oath) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the maner of the garniſhment, and the ſame bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing founde inſufficient, the plaintife ſhalbe reſtored to his lande with the proſites meane.</p>
               <p>We may finde alſo in ſuch reall actions an oath required in another maner, but yet to good purpoſe, that is, to take away vnneceſſarie delayes of Iuſtice. For if the tenaunt in a <hi>praecipe</hi> of lande will caſt an Eſſoyne of the Kings ſeruice, the Eſſoygner ſhall ſweare, and that directlie, the ſame to be no feined excuſe, otherwiſe the Eſſoyne ſhall not be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed. Some fewe other particular caſes of like nature may peraduenture be ſhewed where an othe is admitted or required in theſe reall actions, but none I am ſure tending to anie ſuch purpoſe as theſe oathes commaunded and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forced <hi>ex officio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In criminall cauſes and ſuytes,
<note place="margin">Criminall cauſes.</note> whereby eyther the loſſe of life, libertie, member of the bodie, or good name, may enſue (which among worldlie things are moſt deare and pretious vnto men) the common lawes of this lande haue wholie forborne (and that for juſt reſpectes) to vrge or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an oath vpon the accuſed. For in wiſedome it was foreſeene that the frailtie of man for the ſafetie of life, the preſeruation of libertie, credite, and eſtimation would not ſpare to prophane euen that which is moſt holie, and by committing ſinfull perjurie, caſt both ſoule and bodie in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternall perdition.</p>
               <p>This knewe the ſubtill ſerpent our aduerſarie full well in generall, although he were deceyued in the particular, when as he ſaide vnto God concerning the holie man Iob: <hi>Skinne for skinne,
<note place="margin">Iob cap. 2.</note> and whatſoeuer a man hath, will hee giue for him ſelfe and for his life, but ſtretch out thy hande</hi> (ſayth Sathan) <hi>and touche his bones and his fleſhe, and ſee if he will not then blaspheme thee to thy face.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:13213:18"/>
Moreouer, euerie wiſe Magiſtrate may well conceyue vpon howe weake and feeble a foundation he ſhall ground his ſentence, truſting to ſuch an oath, when before hande the ſuſpition and preſumption of perjurie is ſo pregnant. Therefore in cauſes capitall or otherwiſe criminall, theſe our lawes neyther vrge by oathe nor force by torment any man to accuſe or excuſe him ſelfe, but rejecte the oath as vnbeſeeming a well gouerned ſtate or common wealth: And condemne the torture as a thing moſt cruel &amp; barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, wherof although they neede no other proofe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the dailie practize and proceedinges againſt parties ſuſpected of ſuch offences, yet concerning the inquiſitions by tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we may ſee the ſame affirmed by that learned Iudge Maiſter <hi>Forteſcue</hi> in his commentaries of the Pollicie of this Kingdome,
<note place="margin">49. Ed. 3.</note> And for th'other there are ſufficient au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities in the reportes of the lawes them ſelues: therfore in the booke of Aſſizes it appeareth, that diuers Iurours were challenged as leſſe indifferent, ſome for matters that founded to their reproach and diſhoneſtie, as that corrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie they had taken money of one of the parties in the ſuite, whervpon it was ordered by the Iuſtices, that ſuch as were challenged for cauſes not diſhoneſt, ſhould bee ſworne to declare the trueth, the other for the reaſon aforeſaide, not to be examined at all, but the challenge to be tried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their oath, The ſame lawe is againe reported vnto vs Anno 49. Ed. 3. fol. 1. Vpon the like reaſon is the refolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the chiefe Iuſtices &amp; of the Iudges <hi>Saunders</hi> and <hi>Whid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">12. R. Eliz.</note> That if a bill of perjurie committed in the Chaunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re againſt the forme of the ſtatute made in the fifte yeare of her Maieſties reigne, were exhibited in the ſame Court, that the defendent ſhould not be compelled to make aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vpon his oath eyther to bill or intertogatories, but that the parties ought to deſcende to yſſue, and the triall to be had by Iurie in the Kings Benche. I ſhall not neede to ſpende time in declaring after the parties in ſuite haue ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned yſſue triall by Iurie howe many wayes an oath is vſed about the triall of ſuch matters of fact, as the oath of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors them ſelues. and of their triars vpon challenge, or to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:13213:19"/>ſpeake any thing of the oath to be miniſtred vnto ſuck as require the ſuertie of peace, neither to diſcourſe of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of homage or fealtie by the tenaunt to the Lord, ſince theſe and ſuch like are well known to euery one, although but of meane judgement, to bee neceſſarilie vſed for the better adminiſtration of Iuſtice, and aſſuraunce of dueties, making nothing at all for thoſe phantaſticall and offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous oathes and examinations, proceeding rather <hi>ab officio</hi> the verbe, then <hi>ex officio</hi> the nowne.</p>
               <p>Neyther is it neceſſarie to ſet forth at large where and in what particular caſes Oathes are appointed by Actes of Parliament of this Realme, as to remember the diuers Oathes of Biſhops, Counſellours, Iudges, Magiſtrates, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and Miniſters of Lawe and Iuſtice. The oath ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned for the maintenaunce of the ſupremacie Royall, and aboliſhing of forreine juriſdiction. The power of exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation by oath by the ſtatute of Anno 5. H. 4. and manie others, for that by peruſall of the ſtatutes, the ſame may vnto him that will ſearche, eaſilie appeare. Vpon conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all which actes of Parliament, beeing in force, it may truelie be affirmed that there is not ſo much as a bare ſhewe or ſhadowe of matter to giue credite or allowaunce to theſe infinite wreſted and extorted oathes <hi>ex officio.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it may be that ſome man in the defence of the cauſe and for allowance of thoſe oathes will alleadge the twiſe damned and repealed ſtatute made vpon the ſiniſter ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of the Cleargie Anno 2. H 4. cap. 15.
<note place="margin">The ſtatute againſt hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie 2. H. 5.</note> Which bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die and broyling lawe gaue authoritie to Dioceſans, to cauſe the perſons defamed or euidentlie ſuſpected of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed hereſie, to be arreſted, and vnder ſafe cuſtodie to be deteyned in their Priſons, till they of the articles laide to their charge, did cannonicallie purge them ſelues, or els abjure it according to the lawes of the Church. And did appoint the proceeding and determination of the cauſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the arreſted, to be according to the effect of the law and cannonicall decrees. For aunſwere wherevnto I ſaye, that although the ſword by that ſtature lawe was commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into the handes of madde men, and the ſeelie lambes
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:13213:19"/>deliuered ouer to the greedie and deuouring woolues, yet doeth it not appeare by any apparaunt or expreſſe wordes of that law, that any authoritie was therby giuen or meant to be giuen to Ordinaries or Iudges Eccleſiaſticall, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any ſuch generall oathe, or otherwiſe to compell by oath the priſonner to become his owne accuſor, for that (and eſpeciallie in caſes of life and death) had bene direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie againſt the lawes and juſtice of this lande. But if it bee alleadged, that the ſame was <hi>tacite</hi> and <hi>incluſiue</hi> allowed by thoſe wordes of cannonicall ſanctions or decrees, and that there be any ſuch, yet the ſame decree beeing againſt the lawes and decrees of God, as before is proued, that ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute was therein no binding lawe, neyther gaue ſufficient warraunt to put in execution any ſuch corrupt courſe of proceeding, ſince all lawes and ordinances of man whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, being repugnaunt to the lawes of God, are meerelie voyde and of none effect, as the learned Saint <hi>Germaine</hi> in his booke of <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Student</hi> hath wel obſerued, where he ſaieth, <hi>That euerie mans lawe must bee conſonant to the lawe of God.</hi> And therefore the lawes of Princes, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of Prelates, the ſtatutes of Communalties, ne yet the ordinances of the Church, is not righteous or obligatorie, Except it be conſonant and agreeable to the lawe of God.</p>
               <p>But as concerning that ſtatute, will you heare what is declared by Parliament Anno 25. H. 8. The ſubjects of this Realme at that time lamentablie ſhewe vnto their Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord and King,
<note place="margin">Ca. 14.</note> howe that ſtatute was impetrate &amp; obteined (I vſe the wordes of the lawe) by the ſuggeſtion of the Cleargie of this Realme, not declaring or defininge any certen caſes of hereſie, that thoſe wordes (canonicall ſanctions or decrees) were ſo generall, that vnneth the moſt expert and beſt learned men of the Realme (diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie lying in wayte vpon him ſelfe) could eſchewe and auoyd the penaltie and daunger of that act. And canonicall ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions if he ſhould be examined vpon ſuch captious Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatories (note I pray you) as is and hath bene accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to bee miniſtred by the Ordinaries of the Realme in
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:13213:20"/>caſes where they will ſuſpect any perſon of hereſie.</p>
               <p>They moreouer affirme, that it ſtandeth not with the right order of juſtice nor good equitie, that any perſon ſhould be conuict &amp; put to the loſſe of his life, good name, or goodes, vnleſſe it were by due accuſation and witneſſe; or by preſentment, verdict, confeſſion, or proceſſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawrie: Declaringe moreouer, that by the lawes of the Realme for treaſons committed to the perill of the Kinges moſt Royall Maieſtie, vpon whoſe ſuertie dependeth the wealth of the whole Realme, no perſon can ne may be put to death, but by preſentment, verdict, or proceſſe of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawrie: and therfore not reaſonable that any Ordinarie by any ſuſpition conceyued of his owne fantafie, without due accuſation or preſentment, ſhould put any ſubject of this Realme, in the infamie or ſlaunder of hereſie, to the perill of life, loſſe of name, and goods. They further ſhewe that there may be hereſies and paines and puniſhmentes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ordeined in and by the canonicall ſanctions, and by the lawes and ordinances made by the Popes and Biſhops of Rome, and by their authorities, for holdinge, doing, preaching or ſpeaking of things contrartie to the ſaide canonicall ſanctions, lawes and ordinances, whiche be but humane, mere repugnant and contrarious to the Prerogatiue of the Kings Imperiall Crowne. Regall juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, lawes, ſtatutes, and ordinaunces of the Realme, by reaſon whereof the people of the ſame for obſeruing, maintayning, defending, and due executing of the Kinges lawes, ſtatutes, and prerogatiue Royall, by authoritie of that act, may be brought into ſlaunder of hereſie, to their great infamie and daunger and perill of their liues. So wee ſee firſt howe the craftie and ſubtill Cleargiemen were the procurers of that ſtatute lawe, to the ende that they might execute their crueltie, and howe vnder cloked and couert termes of canonical ſanctions, they vnjuſtlie vſurped juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction ouer the people, miniſtring vnto them captious &amp; ſnarling Interrogatories. And (as it ſhould ſeeme by the hiſtories) vpon oath contrarie to the true meaning of the lawe and law makers, and againſt the right order of juſtice
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:13213:20"/>and all good equitie: impugning thereby the Royall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue, th'Imperiall Crown, the Princelie Scepter, lawes and Pollicie of this Kingdome. In conſideration where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, and to take from them all coulor of lawe poſitiue of this Realme, that ſtatute was then repealed, and a newe forme of enquirie of hereſie by indightment, preſentment or due accuſation by two lawfull witneſſes at the leaſt, was eſtabliſhed.</p>
               <p>And it is further to be noted, that although the Statute made Anno 31. H. 8. commonlie called the ſtatute of ſixe articles, was a verie ſtreight, ſore, extreeme &amp; terrible act,
<note place="margin">31. H. 8. c. 14</note> as the ſtatute of the repeale thereof ſpeaketh, yet finde wee not by that lawe, or any other, theſe generall oathes or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aminations by oath <hi>ex officio</hi> of perſons ſuſpected or accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for hereſie or other cryme Eccleſiaſticall,
<note place="margin">1. Ed. 6. c. 16</note> to be enacted or allowed of, but rather by the courſes and fourmes of enquire and triall otherwiſe preſcribed in this and other ſtatutes, the ſame is rejected and diſallowed whollie as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt and full of iniquitie. For by this ſtatute of ſixe articles, commiſſions are appointed to be directed to the Archb. or Biſhop of the Dioceſſe, and to his Chauncellor or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſarie, and ſuch other as the Kinge ſhould appoint, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinge them power to take information and accuſation, (not by oath of the partie conuented) but by the oathes &amp; depoſitions of two able and lawfull perſons at the leaſt, or to enquire by the oathes of xij. men. Giuing alſo to the Ordinaries power and authoritie to enquire in their viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Senis, and to take accuſations and informations as in forme aforeſaide, and not otherwiſe. The maner alſo of proceſſe againſt the perſons indighted, accuſed or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, is there preſcribed. And the forme of proceedinge vpon apparaunce of the partie appointed to bee not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe vnjuſt examinations by oath <hi>ex officio,</hi> but accordinge to the lawes of the Realme, and th'effect of that act.</p>
               <p>And although at that tyme this ſtatute lawe ſeemed juſt and equall, as concerning the maner of enquirie and trial, yet time (diſcloſing all thinges) made it appeare that the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13213:21"/>ſame was not falſe, in reſpect that diuers ſecret and vntrue accuſations and preſentementes might bee, and by all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihoode were maliciouſlie conſpired, and therefore it was enacted Anno 35. H. 8. cap. 5. That no perſon ſhould bee arraigned or put to triall for or vpon any accuſation, infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or preſentment, concerning any of the offences mentioned in the ſtatute of 6. articles, but onely vppon ſuch preſentementes and indightements as ſhoulde bee ſounde and made by the oathes of 12. men or moe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Theſe things ſtanding thus, howe may any man juſtifie or defende (much leſſe practize) thoſe generall oathes or examinations by oath <hi>ex officio</hi> by any ſtatute lawe of this Realme, being by them not onelie rejected, but vtterlie condemned as not ſtanding with the right order of Iuſtice nor good equitie, eſpeciallie the ſtatute made Anno 25. H. 8. beinge in force and limitinge vnto Archb. and Biſh. none other juriſdiction then ſuch as they may vſe without offence to the Prerogatiue Royall and the lawes and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of this Realme. Of which lawes and cuſtomes the common lawe is no part or portion. And as a well-willer I would aduiſe all Ordinaries and ſuch as exerciſe Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall juriſdiction, eſpeciallie hauing taken the oathe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned for the maintenaunce of the Supremacie Royall, (wherein they ſweare to aſſiſt to their power, and defende all juriſdictions, Priuiledges, Preheminences and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties graunted or belonging to the Queenes Highnes, her heyres and ſucceſſours, or vnited and annexed to the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Crowne of this Realme) to take heede that they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt not to put in practize or exerciſe any ſuch Oathes or examinations <hi>ex officio,</hi> leaſt happilie they bee not onely founde thereby to be impugnors of the Royall Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiues, but diſcredited farther by the breach of their oath.</p>
               <p>If it be ſaide (for what will not be moued for a defence) that the King heretofore gaue in thoſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions beſides the lettre and meaning of the ſtatute of 6.
<note place="margin">The Kings commiſſion</note> Articles, power and authoritie by expreſſe words vnto the Commiſſioners Eccleſiaſticall to examine by oath the perſons accuſed or preſented. As that is not likelie, neither as I ſuppoſe can
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:13213:21"/>be proued, So (admitting it were true, and that ſuch kind of oathes were conſonant to the lawe of God) yet were the ſame no ſufficient or lawfull juſtification, inaſmuch as we haue prooued, and further ſhal prooue ſuch examinations and inquiries vpon oath, to be injurious both to the Prince and people of this Realme, and to impugne our gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and forme of Iuſtice. In which caſes the Kings grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t or commiſſion is of no force in lawe. For as <hi>Bracton</hi> well hath written, <hi>Potestas Principis juris est no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> injuriae, &amp; cùm ipſo ſit author juris, non debet inde injuriarum naſci occaſio vnde jura naſcuntur.</hi> That the King by his Commiſſion or graunt, or otherwiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Parliament, may not change or alter the lawes of this Realme, nor the order, maner or fourme of adminiſtration of Iuſtice, is rightlie alſo noted vnto vs by that graue and learned Iudge Maiſter <hi>Forteſcue,</hi> ſaying: <hi>Non potest Rex Angliae ad libitum ſuum leges mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare Regni ſui Principatu, namque nedum Regali ſed &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litico ipſe ſuo populo dominatur.</hi> And by the booke alſo of Anno 11. H. 4. where it is agreed that neither the King by his graunt, nor the Pope by his Bulles (for all his triple Crowne) can change or alter the lawes of the lande, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto concurre diuers other bookes of the report of the lawe. Worthie alſo of remembraunce is that ſaying of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice <hi>Scroope</hi> Anno 1. Ed. 3. fol. 26. <hi>If the King</hi> (ſayeth hee) <hi>commaunde any thing impoſſible that which the lawe will in the caſe must be done?
<note place="margin">49. Ed. 3. 36. H. 6.</note> if he commaunde any thinge contrarie to lawe, his Iustices ought not to doe it.</hi> Anno 42. Ed. 3. There was a Commiſſion awarded out of the Chauncerie to apprehende a certen ſubject of this Realme, and to ſeize his goods and chattells, no enditement, ſuite of partie, or other due proceſſe of lawe precedent, and the ſame was by the Iuſtices holden to be altogither voyde, as a matter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Pollicie of the Realme, and maner of execution of juſtice. Likewiſe it appeareth in the ſame yeare, that a writte proceeding from the Chauncerie, to enquire of Chaunperties, Conſpiracies, &amp;c. whereby one of the Kings ſubjectes ſtood indighted, was by Iuſtice <hi>Kneuet</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the reſolution of the reſt of the Iudges, damned &amp; ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:13213:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:13213:22"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:13213:23"/>voyd in reſpect that ſuch matters are not inquirea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble by writ, but by Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>But it wilbe ſaid of ſome (I verily ſuppoſe) that although neither the common lawes, nor ſtatutes of this Realme, nor the Kings commiſſion, doe or can warrant ſuch maner of oath and examinations <hi>ex officio,</hi> yet the publique prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize and vſe of the honorable Courtes of Starchamber &amp; Chauncerie, the one in cauſes criminall, the other in ſuites ciuill of equitie and conſcience concurring in one forme of taking aunſweres and examinations by oath, doe forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and confirme the thing which wee impugne. Whiche ſpeach as it may ſeeme at the firſt to giue ſome coulor and ſhewe of credit to their cauſe, ſo vppon conſideration had and due comparing the one with the other, it will ſoone appeare to be but a vaniſhing ſmoake, and ſhadowe voyde of ſubſtance. For firſt, if it ſhould bee graunted, that ſuch kinde of oathes and examinations were vſed in the Courts of Starchamber and Chauncerie, yet would it not followe that the ſame might be practized in the Courtes and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories Eccleſiaſticall, vnleſſe the like allowance thereto and conſent of the whole Realme might be prooued alſo. And who knoweth not howe weake a profe, examples, and preſidentes are where an expreſſe lawe or certen policie is to the contrarie. Therefore it is well ſaid in the ciuill lawe, <hi>Jus non ex regula ſumatur, ſed ex jure regula fiat.</hi> By better Logick might they conclude thus: All anſweres are made vpon oath in the Kings Courtes of Starchamber &amp; Chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerie, <hi>Ergo</hi> the ſame courſe may be vſed in the Courtes of the Kings Bench and common place, which neuertheleſſe were an abſurd concluſion. It is verie true in deede, that theſe honorable Courtes of Starchamber and Chauncerie proceede not to the tryall of cauſes by Iurie, after the manner of the common lawes of this Realme, but giue their judgementes and definitiue ſentence vppon the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere and examination of the defendent, affirmed by his corporall oathe, and vpon the depoſitions of witneſſes. But who hath euer ſeene in theſe Courtes any ſubject of
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:13213:23"/>this lande, in a cauſe concerning him ſelfe, brought forth and compelled to depoſe or make aunſwere vppon his oath, no bill of complainte or information formerlie ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited againſt him. Nay on the contrarie, theſe Courtes obſeruing the due forme of Iuſtice, enforce no man to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, but where hee hath a knowne accuſor, and perfect vnderſtandinge of the cauſe or cryme objected, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall is permitted to haue a coppie of the bill of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainte or information (beeing not <hi>ore tenus,</hi>) And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed moreouer both tyme conuenient, and counſell lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned well to conſider and aduiſe of his oathe and aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. And if his aduerſaries complaint bee either inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in forme or matter, or ſuch as the Court hath no juriſdiction to determine the defendent vppon demurrer, without oathe is diſmiſſed, and that with coſtes. And ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitt the accuſation, ſuch as euery way is aunſwerable, yet if the Interr. miniſtred, bee impertinent to the matter of complaint, the defendent without offence to the Court, may refuſe to make aunſwere to the ſame. What ſimili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude or likenes then is there betweene the oathes and exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations vſed in theſe honorable Courtes, and thoſe conſtreiners <hi>ex officio,</hi> ſince the former ſorte bee orderlie taken in Courtes of Iuſtice, th'other without all courſe of judgement, th'one where pl. and complaint are manifeſt, the other where neyther accuſor nor matter of accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion doe appeare, the one oath made vppon certen know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and good aduiſement, the other ſoddenlie without all diſcretion vpon vncertaine demaundes, the one wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie reſtrained to certen limittes and boundes, the other fooliſhlie wandringe at the doubtfull will of a ſlie and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till appoſer. Vpon the one the deponent aunſwereth to the accuſation of his aduerſarie, by the other hee is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled oftentimes to bee his owne accuſor and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner: the one enquireth an aunſwere to matter in fact, done eyther to the injurie of ſome priuate perſon, or hurte of the publique ſtate, the other conſtreyneth the reuealing of wordes, deedes, and thoughtes, though neuer offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to any.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:13213:24"/>
Than ſince it is apparaunt that theſe manner of oathes are altogither mere ſtraungers to our pollicie,
<note place="margin">The practiſe of the clear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gie.</note> and not ſo much as once countenaunced by any lawe, cuſtome, ſtatut or Court of this Realme: Howe then &amp; by whoſe meanes hath this alien heretofore intruded as a troubleſome gueſt into the houſe of the common wealth? This partlie as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, hath bene declared with ſome griefe of minde, by that godlie ſeruaunt of Chriſt <hi>Iohn Lambert,</hi> who noteth the papiſticall Cleargie and religious men of his time moſt irreligiouſlie to haue practized the ſame. And no doubt the Prelates of former ages, fayning and pretendinge ſuch oathes to be neceſſarie for the gouernment of the church, and to purge the Prouince of euill men, as aforeſaide. But in trueth, finding it a fitt inſtrument to maintaine the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhe Hierarchie, and to tyrannize ouer the conſciences of good men, moſt impiouſlie violating the lawes both of God and man, impoſed this maner of corrupt oath vppon the people, and no mervaile, ſince there was no euil or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe that could bee deuiſed, either againſt the Prince, people or pollicie of this lande, which theſe kinde of our Prelates haue not attempted and put in practize. For firſte diſguiſing themſelues vnder the viſor and maſke of hipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie and feined holines, and making marchandize of all thinges (euen of heauen and hell) purchaſed and acquired in ſhort time (ſuch was the blinde deuotion of the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious laitie) great and large Seignories, Landes and poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions (the verie mother and nource of pryde, preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and vaine pompe of this worlde) And not ſo ſatisfied, but vnſaitablie and moſt ambitiouſlie luſting after rule &amp; dominion, ſpared not againſt their due alleadgance, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt euen the Kings and Princes of the lande. Lett the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention and ſtrife of <hi>Anſelme,</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie</hi> with King <hi>Rufus,</hi> the manifolde practizes of <hi>Thomas, Bec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket</hi> againſt King Henrie the ſeconde, the tragicall life, and pitifull ende of King <hi>John,</hi> occaſioned chieflie by the mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious meanes of the Archbiſhop <hi>Stephen Langton,</hi> the trea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon of Archbiſhop <hi>Arundell</hi> againſt his ſoueraigne Lorde and King Richard the ſecond, and the pryde and inſolencie
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:13213:24"/>of Cardinall <hi>Woolſey</hi> againſt that renowmed Prince Kinge H. 8. among others, be ſufficient teſtimonies in this behalf. And as theſe pontificall Prelates with others more, puffed vp in ſwelling pryde and ambition, ſtrake at the head, ſo the crewe of that Antichriſtian Cleargie ceaſed not from time to time to wraſtle and make warre euen with the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes and ſtrength of the bodie politike of this Realme, the lawes I meane and cuſtomes of this kingdome, beinge the principall ſtay and ſtoppe to their inſolent and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous attemptes, endeuouring them ſelues to writhe out and exempt them ſelues from their due ſubjectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the ſame, ſometimes againe encroching and vſurping the right and juriſdiction of the Kinges courtes, coueringe to drawe all cauſes into their coſtlie and lingring Conſiſtories. And of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes bringing in (to the prejudice both of the Prince and the people) forreine decrees and conſtitutions, with the corrupt Canons and ceremonies of the accurſed ſea of Rome. For proofe whereof, lette the particular examples hereafter mentioned, ſerue, as a fewe amongeſt manie.</p>
               <p>The Pope (ſayeth <hi>Polidore <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgill</hi>) made a lawe in the Counſell of <hi>Lyons,</hi> that the Cleargie ſhould not bee taxed without his leaue or commaundement: which lawe of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munitie, although it were of no force to binde within this Realme, for that the ſame is not ſubject to any foreine made lawes or conſtitutions not ſuffred by the King, and voluntarilie accepted and vſed by his people, as is expreſlie declared by the ſtatute made Anno 25. H. 8. cap. 21. yet ſee the good diſpoſition and obedience of the Cleargiemen of this Realme in the time of King Ed. 1. which Churchmen with great obſtinacie refuſed to paye the ſubſidie graunted to the King. <hi>Robert,</hi> then Archbiſh. of <hi>Canterburie</hi> (head &amp; primate of that faction) wickedlie abuſing this text of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſcripture to ſerue his rebellious intent, <hi>obedire oportet Deo magis quam hominibus,</hi> The Pope and his purſle bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his beſt beloued Gods: Howe much better and more Biſhoplike might he haue remembred, <hi>Date quae ſunt Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaris Caeſari, &amp; quae ſunt Dei Deo.</hi> That holy ſaint <hi>Hugh,</hi>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:13213:25"/>ſometimes Biſhop of <hi>Lincolne,</hi> related amongeſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Gods, puffed vp with the like arrogancie in the time of the ſeuerall Reignes of King H. 2. and Richarde the 1. and of King Iohn, denied the payment of tribute and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidie, bluſtering and puffinge out: moreouer like <hi>Cacus</hi> in his denne his ſmokie blaſtes of curſſe and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Kings collectours, A notable example of humilitie and obedience in a Popeholie Biſhop. It is ſaide alſo by Maiſter <hi>Frowick</hi> Anno 10. H. 7. That the Cleargie had a Conſtitution, that no Prieſt ſhould be impleaded by the common lawe of this Realme, for any cauſe whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer: whether he ſaide truelie therein, lette the Canoniſtes judge. But certain I am, the whole rabble of that Romiſh Cleargie, did from time to time their beſt endeuour to make them ſelues lawleſſe altogither, as by the grieuances exhibited by the Princes of Germanie at the Counſell of <hi>Norrenberg</hi> in the time of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the fifte, may well appeare. And this our haughtie <hi>Hugh</hi> of <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne,</hi> eyther emboldened by ſuch a Cannon, or of his own free courage, as a luſtie champion of that irregular confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracie, drewe out his woodden dagger of excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt the Kings, Iudges, and Magiſtrates, ſecluding them as farre as his follie might, from the fellowſhip and companie of Chriſtians, becauſe they had by courſe of lawe impoſed a fine vpon a Proſelite of theirs, newlie crept into their vnholie orders, for his treſpaſſe committed in the Kings Forreſtes.
<note place="margin">27. H. 8.</note> So likewiſe the reuerende Iudge Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> declared, that in the time of King Henrie the 6. a Biſhop of <hi>Winchester,</hi> being outlawed for no leſſe fault then wilfull murther, and his temporalities therfore ſeized into the Kings handes, refuſed the iudgement of lawe, and ſued to the court of Roome, the Pope writinge to the King in his behalfe, aunſwere was made; that the lawes of this Realme were ſuch: wherevpon as vanquiſhed and driuen from his ſhiftes, the Biſhop ſubmitted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the grace of the King (and though vnworthie) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teined pardon. We heard alſo in the 2. yeare of King H. 4.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:13213:25"/>howe the Popes publication or collector tooke vpon him by vſurpation of authoritie, to take both oath and obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a certain Vicar, to holde him ſelfe contented with ſuch endowment as the collector had appointed, the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonage being appropriate to the Deanrie of Windſor, and howe the Deane drewe the Vicar into plea before this new founde Iudge the Collector, for the breache both of his oath and bonde. Vpon which wrong done to the Royall juriſdiction, the Vicar complayning, had a Prohibition. In which caſe are principallie to be noted, the vnlawfull im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of an oath by one that was no Magiſtrate, but <hi>quid domini facient audent cum talia fures,</hi> and th'injurious pro ſequting and drawing into plea of the Kinges ſubject be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an incompetent Iudge by this Deane a Cleargie man of the Realme. In like ſorte the Hoſpitallers and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plers, aſſuming to them ſelues juriſdiction in prejudice of the King and of his Crowne, drewe the ſubjectes of this Realme into ſuite before the Conſeruators of their Priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, for cauſes perteyning to the juriſdiction of the Kings Courtes, for reformation whereof the ſtatute of <hi>Westm.</hi> the 2. cap. 43. was ordeyned. Howe rigorous, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious, and intollerable the dealinges <hi>ex officio</hi> by thoſe Prelates and Ordinaries were (whereof theſe examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons by extorted oath were a principall parte) the grieuous complaint of the whole Communaltie of this Realme in the 23. yeare of the reigne of King H. 8. doeth ſufficientlie declare. Whereby the King was enformed, how theſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileſſe Ordinaries by their extraordinarie &amp; lawleſſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, cited and ſommoned his ſubiectes, feyned and framed ſtraunge accuſations againſt them, no accuſers appearing, examined them vpon articles captiouſlie deuiſed for their purpoſe, and in the ende admitting no defence, and diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing all purgation, forced them to abjure, or condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them to the fire, a moſt fearfull and barbarous courſe of inquiſition. Vnto which complaint thoſe Phariſaicall Cleargie men (who will not enter Pilates common Hall, leaſt they ſhould be defiled, and yet crye out with loude
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:13213:26"/>voyce, <hi>Crucifige, crucifige,</hi> made (as to the King him ſelfe there it ſeemed) a verie weake and ſlender defence. And no maruayle, ſince wickedneſſe may more eaſilie be commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, then well defended.</p>
               <p>But will you ſee more fullie and clearelie, beholde as in a glaſſe the manifold vſurpations, incrochmentes, injuries and oppreſſions committed and done from time to time, by the Pope, Prince of that curſſing &amp; accurſed Cleargie, and by his ſworne &amp; deuoted Baalamites and ſhauelinges, againſt the rightes and prerogatiues of this Imperiall Crowne, the lawes of this Monarchie, and the liberties of the ſubjectes thereof, then read and conſider the grieuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the commons exhibited againſt the Cleargie Anno 21. H. 8. the ſeuerall ſtatutes of Prouiſion and Premunire, the ſtatutes of Mortmaine, with the diuers kindes of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibitions to the Courtes and Conſiſtories Eccleſiaſticall. Among which you may finde an eſpeciall prohibition with an attachement therevpon deuiſed againſt theſe injurious oathes and examinations, as againſt abuſes greatlie offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue to the Crowne and dignitie Royall. Which the better ſhall appeare by the writtes them ſelues, which are in this forme ſet downe in the Regiſter,
<note place="margin">Prohibitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> 
                  <hi>Rex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icecomiti ſalutem. Praecipimus tibi quod non permittas quod aliqui Laici ad citationem talis Epiſcopi, aliquo loco conueniant de caetero ad aliquas recognitiones faciendas, vel Sacramentum praestan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, niſi in caſibus Matrimonialibus &amp; Testamentarijs, te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte, &amp;c.</hi> And the Attachement is in this maner: <hi>Rex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ic. ſalutem. Pone per vados, &amp;c. talem Epiſcopum quod ſit cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Justiciarijs nostris, &amp;c. ostenſurus, quare fecit ſummoniri, &amp; per Cenſuras Eccleſiasticas distringi laicos perſonas, vel. laicos homines &amp; foeminas, ad comparendum coram eo, ad praeſtandum juramentum pro voluntate ſua ipſis invitis, in graue praejudicium Coronae &amp; dignit atis nostrae Regiae, nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non contra conſuetudinem Regni nostri, &amp;c.</hi> By the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of which writtes, and eſpeciallie of theſe wordes, <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitiones &amp; ſacramentum pro voluntate ſua,</hi> and <hi>ipſis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitis,</hi> we may plainlie perceyue, howe all theſe inquiries,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:13213:26"/>examinations,
<note place="margin">Hindes caſe and 18. R. Eliz. proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth no leſſe.</note> and ſifting out of matters by oath and by way of inquiſition in the Courtes Eccleſiaſticall, are by the Regall authoritie impugned, and that as prejudicial to the Crowne and dignitie Royall, and the lawes and cuſtomes of this Realme, theſe wordes <hi>pro voluntate ſua,</hi> expreſlie deuoting vnto vs the vſurped officious power, and licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous pleaſure, whereby contrarie to all due courſe of Iuſtice they conſtraine an aoth. And theſe wordes <hi>(ipſis invitis)</hi> manifeſtlie painting out the rigorous, injurious, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulſarie exacting of the ſamo. Moreouer, we ſee it declared by the ſtatute of <hi>Marlebridge,</hi> cap. 23. That no man may compell anie free-holder of this Realme, to ſweare againſt his will, without the Kings precept or commaundement, that is, according to the lawe and Iuſtice of this Realme: for ſo are we taught to vnderſtande the ſame by the booke of Anno 2. R. 3. whereby it is euident, that vnleſſe theſe Ordinaries could prooue their forcing of oathes <hi>ex officio,</hi> to be warranted by authoritie of the lawes and juſtice of this lande (as in trueth they can not) all their dealinges in ſuch caſes, are by the ſame lawes vtterlie diſallowed and condemned.</p>
               <p>But here (me thinkes) ſome retchleſſe or inconſiderate reader ſteppeth forth and ſayeth, What is your meaning to circumſcribe and include all authoritie of miniſtringe oathes in the Courtes Eccleſiaſticall within the ſtreight limites and boundes of cauſes Teſtamentarie and Matri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall, howe then ſhall all other matters ſubiect to their juriſdiction (being in number manie, and in nature diuers) receyue due examination. For aunſwere therevnto, this ſhortlie may ſuffice, That the ſtate of the queſtion whiche at this preſent we haue in hande, is not in what caſes thoſe Courtes may giue or impoſe an oath, but the matter wher of we nowe intreate is, concerning forced and conſtrained oathes <hi>ex officio,</hi> and eſpeciallie in that generall maner be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore remembred. And as touching the triall of cauſes by examination of witneſſes judiciallie depending betweene partie and partie in th'Eccleſiaſticall Courtes, it ſtandeth
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:13213:27"/>firme and for founde lawe, according to the ſaide Prohi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the opinion of Maiſter Iuſtice <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> in his booke of Iuſtice of Peace, is, That thoſe Iudges Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall haue no lawfull power or authoritie to force or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine by cenſures of the Church or otherwiſe, any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Realme, againſt his will to teſtifie vppon his oathe, other then in the foreſaide cauſes of Mariage and Teſtamentes, although comming before them, as produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by the parties in the ſuite, they may lawfullie (as vnto men voluntarilie accepting the ſame) miniſter an oath, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe it is plaine extortion, and wrong vnto the partie. And admitte they would denie to depoſe, what prejudice were that to the Court Chriſten, but rather a faylinge in proofe in the partie ſuing. And in this ſtate and ſorte ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the proofe of cauſes by witneſſes at the common law. Neuertheleſſe, ſince the ſtatute made againſt wilfull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurie, the witneſſe ſerued with proceſſe, and hauinge his charges tendered, making default, incurreth a paine pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niarie. And why ſhould the Cleargie and Iudges Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall thinke it much, to be ruled and reſtrayned concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their juriſdiction by the Kings Prerogatiue, and the common lawes of this Realme, ſince what juriſdiction or authoritie ſoeuer they haue or enjoye (matters of the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine lawe excepted) yea euen in thoſe eſpeciall cauſes of Teſtamentes, Mariages, Diuorſes, and Tythes, is no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe theirs, then by the goodnes of the Princes of this Realme, and by the lawes and cuſtomes of the ſame, as the ſtatute of Anno 24. H. 8. cap, 12. well declareth, and may be taken from them and reſtored to the temporall Iudges, eſpeciallie the abuſes of the Cleargie well deſcruing it at the will and pleaſure of the Prince and people. But to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe to our prohibition and attachment, it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uident thereby, that all the ſommons and citations which thoſe Eccleſiaſtical Iudges ſende forth vnder theſe general termes, <hi>propter ſalute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> animarum,</hi> or, <hi>ex officio mero:</hi> And all their arreſtes, diſtreſſes, impeachmentes, excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and impriſonmentes therevpon enſuing, are altogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:13213:27"/>injurious, both to the Prince and people. And of this opinion ſeemeth to be that learned Iudge Maiſter <hi>Fitzher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> who in his booke <hi>De natura breuium,</hi> ſayeth vppon theſe writtes in this maner: By this appeareth, that theſe generall citations which Bb. make to cite men to appeare before them <hi>pro ſalute animae,</hi> without expreſſing any cauſe eſpeciall, are againſt the lawe. And true it is, for by the ſtatute of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Magna Charta.</note> (conteyninge many excellent lawes of the liberties and free cuſtomes of this Kingdome) It is ordeyned, that no free man be apprehended, impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, diſtrained or impeached, but by the lawe of the lande: and by the ſtatute made Anno 5. Ed. 3. ca. 9. It is enacted, That no man ſhall be attached vpon any accuſation con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the forme of the great Charter, and the lawe of the Realme. Moreouer it is accorded by Parliament Anno 43. E. 3. ca. 9. for the good gouernement of the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naltie, That no man be put to aunſwere, without preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment before Iuſtices, or matter of recorde, or by due pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, or by writt originall, after the auncient lawe of this Lande. And howe then ſhall that kinde of proceedinge <hi>ex officio</hi> by forced oathes, &amp; the vrging of this general oath, and ſtreight impriſoning of ſuch as refuſe to ſweare, bee juſtifiable. If theſe things were not, yet a man would haue thought that at the leaſt the ſharpe and ſeuere ſtatutes of Prouiſion and Premunire, ſo offenſiue to popiſhe Polidore and ſuch like,
<note place="margin">Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire.</note> ſhould haue ſtaied and ſtopt the violent courſe of thoſe injurious inquiſitions, examinations, and wreſted oathes <hi>ex officio.</hi> For, no doubt, the Ordinaries &amp; Cleargiemen practizing the ſame, are all offendors, &amp; doe incur the forfaitures of thoſe penal lawes. For profe wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, let vs conſider the wordes of the ſtatute of Premunire, made Ann<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 16. Ri. 2. ca. 5. and the judgments &amp; expoſitions thervpon had, that ſtatute reciting firſt the grieuous com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the whole Realm againſt the Pope of Rome, who impeached many Patrons in the preſentations to their Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall benefices, excommunicated the Bb. of this realme, for executing the kings writts <hi>de Clerice admitten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do,</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:13213:28"/>ſought to tranſlate ſome of them againſt their and the Kings will, and diuers other inconueniences, in derogation of the Kings Crowne and Regalitie, prouideth remedie for thoſe and ſuch like miſchiefes, in this maner: That if any purchaſe, or purſue, or doe to be purchaſed or purſued in the Court of Rome, or elſwhere, any ſuch tranſlations, proceſſe &amp; ſentences of excommunications, bulles, inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, or any other thinges whiche touche the Kinge, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, his Crowne, and his Regalitie, or his Realme, or them receyue, or make thereof notification, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther execution within the ſame Realme or without, that they, their Notaries, Procurators, Mainteiners, Abbetters, Fautors, and Counſellors, ſhalbe put out of the Kings pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, and their landes and tenementes, goods and chat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telles forfait to the King, &amp;c. Since the making of whiche ſtatute, it hath bene helde and adjudged for cleere lawe in the Kinges Courtes, That if any ſubject of the kinges ſue or impleade an other in any Eccleſiaſticall Court of this Realme, for any cauſe or matter appertayninge to the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination and judgement of the Courtes of the common lawe, or any judge Eccleſiaſticall preſume to holde plea thereof, or deale in any cauſes not belonginge to his juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, that they incurre the daunger and penaltie of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire, as by the booke of 5. Ed. 4. fol. 6. &amp; by th'opinion of the Court Anno 11. H. 7. remembred by Maiſter <hi>Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert,</hi> plainelie doeth appeare. According alſo therevnto is the caſe of Maiſter <hi>Barloo,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Bathe,</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Maiſter Iuſtice <hi>Brooke,</hi> Which Biſh. in the time of Kinge Edwarde the 6. depriuing the Deane of Welles, whoſe Deanrie was a donatiue, paſſing therein beyonde the limites of his juriſdiction, fell into the daunger of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire. And being called into queſtion, and hauinge no juſt defence, was faine to appeale to the Kings mercie, and obteyned a pardon. And that booke of 5. E. 4. before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred, ſetteth downe the reaſon, noting theſe wordes of this ſtatute <hi>(in curia Romana vel alibi)</hi> In which wordes <hi>(alibi)</hi> ſayeth that booke, is intended the Courtes of Bb.
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:13213:28"/>So that if a man be exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate in any of their Courts for a thing which apperteyneth to the Royal Maieſt. that is to ſay (ſayeth that booke) in a matter of the common lawe, the partie excommunicate ſhall haue a premunire facias, and ſo was it adjudged. In whiche wordes among other, is ſpeciallie to be noted, that when ſo euer a wrong or injurie is offered to the common lawe of this lande, there the Kinge is ſaide to be touched, and his Royall Maieſtie impeached. For accordinge to the Princelie ſpeach of that moſt Noble King Ed. 3. in the ſtatute of Prouiſion made in the 38. yeare of his raigne, the Kinges Regalitie chieflie conſiſteth in this, <hi>To ſusteine his people in peace and tranquillitie, and to gouerne them according to the lawes, vſages, and franchiſes of this Lande, wherevnto he is bounde by his ſacred oath made at his Coronation.</hi> If then by vſurping cognizance of plea, in cauſes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the common lawe, and the juriſdiction of the Kinges Courtes, the Eccleſiaſticall Iudges touch the King in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pite,</hi> doe againſt him, his Crown, Regalitie &amp; Realme, &amp; ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequentlie incurre the forfeiture &amp; penalties of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munire: Howe much more doe they touch the King, nay rather lay violent handes on him, &amp; impugne his Royall Throne and Scepter, who contrarie to the Pollicie, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Freedomes of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yea the lawe of God it ſelfe, enforce &amp; conſtraine by cenſure of excommunication &amp; otherwiſe, the Kings people to appeare before them, and extort from them an oath to accuſe them ſelues. And for more plaine demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration (if plainer may be) put the caſe that a Iudge, Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, or Commiſſioner, authoriſed by the Kinge to exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute juſtice according to the lawes of this Realme, ſhould take vpon him by colour of his office and authoritie to conuent the Kings people before him, and vppon their apparaunce to offer vnto them this general oath to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere vnto all ſuch queſtions as him ſelfe ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounde, playing in cauſes criminall the part both of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſor and Iudge, or ſeekinge by oath and captious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogatories,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:13213:29"/>matter of accuſation, wherevppon to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede to condemnation, and to commit the partie refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſuch oath, to ſtreight priſon without bayſe or main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe, could any man juſtifie this his doing to ſtande with lawe or juſtice? Nay rather, might not euerie man juſtlie cry out againſt him, as againſt a ſubuerter of lawe and judgement, and a hatefull enimie to our pollicie &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, yea ſhould not that bee verified of him, which is recorded in the judgement againſt Sir <hi>William Thorp,</hi> ſometime chiefe Iuſtice of Englande, for his cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt dealing, which is, that as muche as in him laye, he had broken the oath which the King is bounde to keepe towardes his people. If all this may truelie be affirmed of ſuch a one, howe then ſhall the Eccleſiaſticall Iudges, practizing in their Courtes and Tribunal Seates, the ſelf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſame vnjuſt and vnlawfull manner of proceeding againſt the Kings people, eſcape the ſeuere ſentence of law, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing them offenſiue touchers, and violaters of the King, and injurious dealers againſt his Regalitie, Crown and Kingdome, &amp; ſo conſequentlie worthie to ſuffer the paines and penalties declared in this ſtatute of Premu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire. That this is no newe opinion or conſtruction, wee finde the reſolution of that learned man Saint <hi>Germaine,</hi> in his booke of <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Student</hi> well agreeing, where he writeth in this maner: <hi>Jf any man bee excommunicate in the ſpirituall Court for debt, trespas, or ſuch other thing, as belongeth to the Kings Crowne and to his Royall dignitie, there he ought to be aſſoyled without making any ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for they not onelie offended the partie, in calling him to aunſwere before them of ſuch things as belong to the law of the Realme, but alſo the King, who by reaſon of ſuch ſuites, looſeth a great aduantage, which he might haue of the writs, originalles, judicialls, fines, amerciamentes, and ſuch other thangs, if the ſuites had bene in his Courtes accordinge to his lawes.</hi> Hee ſheweth further, <hi>That if the Eccleſiasticall Iudges will not make the partie his letters of abſolutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> where hee ought, the partie ſhall haue his action against him.</hi> Hee
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:13213:29"/>affirmeth alſo, <hi>The Lawe to bee according where a man is accurſed</hi> (he meaneth excommunicate) <hi>for a thinge that the Judge had no power to accurſe him in, notwithstandinge that he may haue his ſuite of premunire facias.</hi> Againe we reade howe the late Cardinall <hi>Woolſey,</hi> the Popes Legate here in Englande, erected a newe Court or Conſiſtorie called <hi>The Court of the Legate,</hi> in which he tooke vppon him to proue Teſtamentes, and to heare and determine cauſes in prejudice of the juriſdiction Eccleſiaſticall of this Realme. And howe by his vſurped power Legatiue, he gaue and beſtowed benefices by preuention, to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inheritance of the Kings ſubjectes, and vifiting the ſtate Eccleſiaſticall, vnder coulor of reformation, gained to him ſelfe exceeding great treaſure. But this loftie height of vnlawfull authoritie, weake and feeble in foundation, could not long continue, For in the one and twentieth yeare of the reigne of King Henrie the eight, this proude prieſte with all his glorious pompe and glittering ſhewe of all his Croſſes, Siluer Pillers, guylt Axes, imbrodered Cloakbagges, and purple Hattes, was attainted by his owne confeſſion, in a Premunire, and the next yeare fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, all the Lordes ſpirituall, hauinge deſerued the ſame paines and puniſhmentes for their vnjuſt mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and ſupportation, were called to aunſwere in the Kinges Benche, and knowing them ſelues guiltie, before their day of appearaunce, exhibited to the Kinge their humble ſubmiſſion, joyninge therevnto an offer of a 100000. pounde, to purchaſe their peace, whiche after much ſuite, the King accepted, and by Parliament gaue them a pardon. If then this Romiſh Legate, for aſſuming to him ſelfe juriſdiction by authoritie Papall, in prejudice not of the Kinges Courtes, but of the Courtes Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call (neuertheleſſe to the hurt of the Royall Maieſtie) and for diſturbaunce of the rightes and inheritaunce of the Kinges ſubjectes, fell into the daunger and penaltie of Premunire, and all the Biſhops and Ordinaries of this Realme likewiſe, through their maintayning onelie and
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:13213:30"/>ſupporting the ſame, may we not ſafelie conclude that the Biſhops and Ordinaries in theſe dayes vſurping pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and juriſdiction in like ſorte and maner (although not in the ſame particulars) by coulor of Antichriſtian de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, or practizing thoſe popiſhe Cannons, the verie head of that helliſhe <hi>Cerberus</hi> of Rome (as a learned man well termed them) and the ſinewes of his tyrannicall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, repugnant to the Royall Maieſtie and Pollicie of this Realme, that is to ſay, forcing vnjuſtlie the people of this lande, to ſuch vnlawfull oathes and examinations as are before remembred (injuriouſlie touching thereby the Prince in her Regalitie, and her people in their lawfull libertie wherevnto they are inheritable, matters of more waight and moment, then the hinderaunce of the Biſh. juriſdiction or loſſe of a preſentment to a benefice) doe incurre the penalties and forfaitures limited by the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide ſtatute of Premunire.</p>
               <p>If any man neuertheleſſe vrge and contende, that theſe thinges are juſtifiable by force of the Popes teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (the Cannon and Pontificall lawe I meane) of long time practized,
<note place="margin">Cannon lawe.</note> &amp; continuallie vſed within this Realme, giuing a newe probate and allowance thereto, after ſo publique and juſt condemnation, and fyring of them by that famous Clearke and Doctor of the Church <hi>Martin Luther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sleidan.</note> and by the great number of godlie and learned men his aſſociates, as lawes and ordinaunces contumeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous againſt God, injurious to Magiſtrates, and eſpeciallie eſtabliſhed to mainteine Antichriſtian tyrannie, let him knowe, that this Kingdome is not bounde or ſubject to any forreyne made lawes or conſtitutions, not ſuffered by the King, and voluntarilie accepted, and of longe time vſed by his people, as it is well declared by the ſaide ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Anno 25. H. 8. whoſe wordes are theſe: <hi>For where this your graces Realme recognizinge no ſuperiour vnder God but onelie your Grace, hath bene and is free from ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to any mans lawes, but onelie to ſuch as haue bene deuiſed, made and ordeyned within this Realme, for the
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:13213:30"/>wealth of the ſame, or to ſuch other as by ſufferaunce of your Grace, and your Progenitors, the people of this your Realme haue taken at their free libertie, by their owne conſent, to bee vſed among them, and haue bounde them ſelues by long vſe and custome, to the obſeruaunce of the ſame, not as to the obſeruaunce of the lawes of any forreine Prince, Potentate, or Prelate, but as to the accustomed and auncient lawes of this Realme, originallie establiſhed as lawes of the ſame, by the ſaide ſufferaunce, conſentes, and custome, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, &amp;c.</hi> So to proue any forreine made lawe allowable within this Realme, there muſt concurre Tolleration by the Kinge, voluntarie acceptaunce of his people, and a long and a large time of vſage. None of which can be auerred in theſe maner of oathes and examinations. For firſte it may not be ſaide that the King ſuffereth that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>the he expreſlie forbiddeth by his writtes and proceſſe, as offenſiue to his Crowne and Regalitie. Neyther can his people bee ſaide to haue giuen voluntarie conſent thereto, hauing alwayes repyned and often complayned and cryed out againſt it, as a thing intollerable and inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious to their lawfull libertie, the cuſtome pretended, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing euer impugned (and that juſtlie) can create no lawe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full preſcription, nor ſtande for an auncient lawe of this Realme, but being againſt both lawe and reaſon, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but an inveterate error or diſorder.</p>
               <p>If defence be ſought by any Canon or Conſtitution,
<note place="margin">Canon.</note> (theſe oathes being ſo apparauntlie againſt this our ſtate, common wealth and gouernement) I ſee not howe anie Ordinarie, but to his reproache, may once open his mouth therein,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.</hi> Cap. 9.</note> conſidering that in the Parliament hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Anno 25. H. 8. The whole Cleargie of Englande not onelie for them then liuing, but for their ſucceſſors alſo, ſubmitting them ſelues to the Kings Maieſtie, promiſed <hi>(in verbo Sacerdotij)</hi> if that bee ought worth, That they would neuer from thence foorth preſume to attempt, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leadge, claime, or put in ure, or enact, promulge, or exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute any newe Canons, Conſtitutions, Ordinaunces pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinciall
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:13213:31"/>or other, or by what ſoeuer name they ſhould be called in their conuocation without the Kings moſt Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all aſſent or licence.</p>
               <p>And conſidering alſo that in the ſame Parliament by their full conſent, it is enacted and prouided, That no Canons, Conſtitutions, or Ordinaunces, ſhould be made or put in execution within this Realme, by the authoritie of the conuocation of the Cleargie, which ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tratiant or repugnaunt to the Kinges Prerogatiue Royall or the cuſtomes, lawes, or ſtatutes of this Realme, nor to the dammage or hurt of the Kinges Prerogatiue Royall, ſhould ſtill be vſed and executed vntill, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>But notwithſtanding all thoſe prouident and politique lawes and ſtatutes thus for the good of the common wealth wiſelie eſtabliſhed in the great Aſſemblie of the Realme, and notwithſtandinge alſo thoſe ſolemne pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and proteſtations made as aforeſaide, &amp; although in the 12. yeare of the reigne of King <hi>Henrie</hi> the thirde, there was a moſt ſeuere ſentence of curſe and anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tization denounced in the preſence of the King, and the Nobles of this Kingdome by <hi>Boniface,</hi> then Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterburie,</hi> and manie other Biſhoppes, apparelled in their Pontificalibus, againſt all ſuch as thereafter ſhould willinglie, and maliciouſlie, by any craft or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, violate, infringe, diminiſhe, or chaunge ſecretlie or publiquelie, by deede, worde, or counſell, any of the free cuſtomes of this Kingdome, and eſpeciallie thoſe conteyned in the ſaide great Charter, yet the vnbrideled Cleargie men in the Papiſticall time, nothing regarding the good eſtate of this our pollicie, neyther yet terrified by their owne curſing cenſures, and execrations, nor by the ſeuere lawes of Premunire, moſt impudentlie (to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their owne licentious and lordlie luſtes) haue from time to time aſcited &amp; ſommoned by their lawleſſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, and arreſted and attached by their malapart appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritours, meſſengers, and purſeuauntes, the free people of this Realme, by violence drawing them not onelie into their publique Courtes and Conſiſtories, but priuatelie
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:13213:31"/>alſo into ſecrete corners and priuie chambers, forcinge them there with roughe and rigorous termes of diſgrace and reproache, vpon euerie bare ſurmiſe, and vncertaine rumor, to take a corporall oath to bee examined vppon articles captious and deceitfull, ſeekinge thereby moſt vncharitablie for matters of accuſation. Againſt whom if anie man durſt (ſtanding vppon termes of his lawfull libertie) but a little repine and refuſe to ſweare, ſtreight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way he muſt bee committed to priſon, without baile or mainpriſe, there to abide paine <hi>fort et dure,</hi> depriuinge men of that which is more pretious then life it ſelfe, and as it is ſaide in the ciuill lawe, a Iewell ineſtimable, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie I meane, more to be fauoured, then any thing, as the ſame lawe ſpeaketh, tyrannizing in ſuch cruell manner ouer the poore and miſerable people, in their vile and filthie Cole-houſes, murthering Towers and Turrettes, and in their darke and deadlie Dungeons, as no tongue or penne is ſufficient to expreſſe. And whereas the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of this Realme were ordeyned either for the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of ſuch as are by due courſe of lawe condemned, or for reſtraint of perſons ſuſpected, not bayleable for a time conuenient of examination and judiciall procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. Thoſe mercileſſe Magiſtrates voyde of all pitie and compaſſion, after their ſuddaine and raginge commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments for the moſt parte proceeded not to full examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſentence, but after long and miſerable impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonment, in ſo much as it was thought a great fauour, if after one yeares grieuous and ſtreight impriſonment, the poore diſtreſſed partie were called foroth to aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere. At the time of which ſitting in their tribunall Seate (howe gloriouſlie ſoeuer they paint out their ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, to haue God and Iuſtice in their ſight) theſe men, or rather monſters, coueting more the deſtruction of mankinde, then any amendement or reformation of maners, fedde with delight their fierce and cruel mindes, with the pitiefull ſight of pyned, ſicklie, and wretched creatures, they them ſelues in the meane time being fatt and well fedde. And although the heathen Emperours,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:13213:32"/>
                  <hi>Claudius Caligula, &amp;c.</hi> who tooke delight to be preſent at the bloudie tortures &amp; executions of their ſubjectes, &amp; to heare their pitifull groanes and grieuous ſighes (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunding th'executioners ſo to ſtrike, as the condemned might feele himſelfe to die) may worthilie bee termed fierce, cruell and barbarous, accordinge to that ſayinge: <hi>Qui fruitur poena ſerus est,</hi> yet the extreeme crueltie of thoſe men which termed them ſelues Catholiques, and would be accompted true Chriſtians, was more horrible &amp; deteſtable a great deale. In ſo much as they by lingring tormentes of long and painfull impriſonment, exceeded the leyſure vſed by the other in the time of execution, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king from Death his due title of <hi>King of terrors,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king him a welcome friende, that endes ſo manie miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Adde herevnto that the tyrannie of thoſe heathen men, as fullie ſatisfied, ceaſed with the life of the tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, but the crueltie and furie of thoſe Catholiques, as neuer wearied, condemned and put to fire the dead bodies of thoſe whom they before moſte treacherouſlie had ſline and murdered. But as theſe good Paſtors, or rather deuouring Wolues, were in this inexcuſable man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner moſt cruell againſt Chriſtes deare ſeruauntes, ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in ſome other thinges they were as vaine and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. For in this matter of an oath, they haue deuiſed (according to their toying fantaſie) a certaine fooliſhe fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiue ceremonie in the miniſtringe thereof. For the deponent forſooth, muſt laye his three middle fingers ſtretched out right vppon the booke, in ſignification of the holie trinitie and Catholique faith, and his thuinbe and little finger hee muſt put downe-wardes vnder the booke, in token of damnation, both of bodie and ſoule, if hoe ſay not the trueth: the thumbe belike, as the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, repreſenting the heauie maſſe of the bodie, and the little finger, the light and incorporeall ſubſtaunce of the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Howe ſuperſtitious alſo they were concerning this ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie of the booke (little regardinge the true vſe and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:13213:32"/>ende of an oath) as appeareth by the Allegoricall expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion curiouſlie ſet forth by one of their parſonate and counterfeite Prelates, who ſayth, That the circumſtances in the acte of an Oath, are verie great and waightie, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſmuch as hee that ſweareth by a booke, doeth three things. Firſt, as though hee ſhould ſaye, Let that which is written in the booke, neuer doe me good, neyther the newe nor the olde Lawe if I lye in this mine oathe. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condlie, hee putteth his hande vppon the booke, as though hee ſhould ſay: Nor the good worke whiche I haue done profite mee ought before the face of Chriſte, except I ſaye the trueth, which is founded in Chriſte. Thirdlie, he kiſſeth the booke, as though he ſhould ſay, Let neuer the prayers and petitions which by my mouth I haue vttered, auayle me any thing to my ſoules health, if I ſaye not truelie in this mine oath. Yet you muſt take this I ſuppoſe, as meant onelie by this reuerend father, where lay men, or the baſer ſorte of the Cleargie, take an oath. For that bleſſed <hi>Bonner,</hi> not longe ſince hath taught, as this tricke of their lawe, as he termed it, that a Biſhop may ſweare (ſuch is his priuiledge) <hi>inspectis Euangelijs &amp; non tactis,</hi> bare ſight of the booke without touche or kiſſe, will well ynough ſerue his Lordſhippes turne. Againe, the impoſing of oathes vpon the rotten bones, ragges and reliques of their canonized and coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit ſaints, and vpon the Image of the Crucifige, is both fooliſhe and idolatrous.</p>
               <p>But to conclude, leauing theſe vnjuſt and lawleſſe men with their bad practiſes &amp; fonde inventions, I doubt not, by theſe fewe, yet effectuall proofes and authorities, it doeth manifeſtlie appeare vnto all men of vpright and ſounde judgement, That aſwell the impoſinge as the ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of theſe generall oathes, is a prophane abuſinge of the holy Name of God. That the exacting of Oathes <hi>ex officio,</hi> is a great indignitie to the Crowne and Scepter of this Kingdome, and a wrong and injurie to the freedome
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:13213:33"/>and libertie of the ſubjectes thereof. That the ſame is not neceſſarie or profitable to the Church and common Wealth, but hurtfull to them both, brought in onely by the practize of the Popiſhe cleargie, to the prejudice of the publique peace and tranquillitie of this Realme, and that the ſame neuer had any good allowaunce by anie lawe, cuſtome, ordinaunce or ſtature of this Kingdome, neyther yet put in vre or vſe by any ciuill Magiſtrate of this Lande, but as it corruptlie crept in among manie other abuſes, by the ſiniſter practize and pretences of the Romiſh Prelates and Celargie-men, ſo this their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull dealing hath bene from time to time by law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and juſt Authoritie impugned and reſtreined.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:13213:33"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
